<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:base="https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/">
  <title>Blog posts - craigabbott.co.uk</title>
  <subtitle>I write about accessibility and user centred design.</subtitle>
  <link href="https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/"/>
  <updated>2022-11-30T00:00:00Z</updated>
  <id>https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/</id>
  <author>
    <name>Craig abbott</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Making microservices accessible</title>
    <link href="https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/making-microservices-accessible/"/>
    <updated>2022-11-30T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/making-microservices-accessible/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">
      &lt;h1&gt;Making microservices accessible&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve written this post to be comprehensive, which unfortunately makes it a bit longer than usual.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don&#39;t want to read the whole thing, you can use the following links to find the parts you want to read:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/making-microservices-accessible/#what-is-a-microservice&quot;&gt;What is a microservice?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/making-microservices-accessible/#the-crux&quot;&gt;The crux&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/making-microservices-accessible/#examples&quot;&gt;Examples&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/making-microservices-accessible/#the-redirect-approach&quot;&gt;The redirect approach&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/making-microservices-accessible/#context-is-everything&quot;&gt;Context is everything&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/making-microservices-accessible/#transparency-is-good&quot;&gt;Transparency is good&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/making-microservices-accessible/#session-management-is-hard&quot;&gt;Session management is hard&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/making-microservices-accessible/#wcag-considerations&quot;&gt;WCAG considerations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/making-microservices-accessible/#the-api-approach&quot;&gt;The API approach&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/making-microservices-accessible/#are-apis-in-scope&quot;&gt;Are APIs in scope?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/making-microservices-accessible/#data-not-markup&quot;&gt;Data, not markup&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/making-microservices-accessible/#failing-gracefully&quot;&gt;Failing gracefully&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/making-microservices-accessible/#design-patterns-for-the-win&quot;&gt;Design patterns for the win&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/making-microservices-accessible/#conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What is a microservice?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The term &#39;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Microservices&quot;&gt;microservice&lt;/a&gt;&#39; is becoming more and more popular when you look across the Digital landscape of a lot of big organisations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, a microservice is just a small part of the user journey which focuses on one specific task. They&#39;re not end-to-end, they just do one thing and then they hand-off. For example, taking a credit card payment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently attended &lt;a href=&quot;https://govservicedesign.net/&quot;&gt;SD in Gov&lt;/a&gt;, where again, microservices came up a lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I saw a great talk by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/vonRunte&quot;&gt;Fritz Von Runte&lt;/a&gt;, which was beautifully illustrated, well presented, and used the analogy of each microservice being a Lego brick.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea is that each brick is a little self-contained application, and you can very quickly stick them together to build digital services which should, &lt;em&gt;in theory&lt;/em&gt;, just work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/images/post/microservices-lego-bricks.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Fritz Von Runte presenting at SD in Gov. On the screen is a collection of Lego bricks representing a digital service. Each brick is a microservice, such as secure sign-on, eligibility questions, identity verification and decision making system.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several Government departments, and several large organisations I&#39;ve spoken to recently, are all looking at this approach; because, if executed well, it saves time and money, and they create consistency for users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, as more and more organisations try to leverage microservices, the pitfalls of accessibility are perhaps not being fully considered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The crux&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The important part, which the &lt;em&gt;entire&lt;/em&gt; approach is hinged on, is &lt;em&gt;where&lt;/em&gt; you build the user interface.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you take nothing else away from this post, take away this point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where the user interface sits and who owns the codebase is key. If you get it wrong, the entire approach becomes brittle or extremely time consuming to get right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It becomes a single point of failure, and it will also bring down any service which integrates with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/images/post/microservices-single-point-of-failure.webp&quot; alt=&quot;A user flow showing 3 compliant pages, and 1 non-compliant microservice in the middle making the whole thing non-compliant.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To stick with Fritz&#39;s analogy, while it&#39;s easy to make each Lego brick accessible on its own, people often fail to take a step backwards and look at the accessibility of the end-to-end journey once you stick all the bricks together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/TR/WCAG21/&quot;&gt;Web Content Accessibility Guidelines (WCAG)&lt;/a&gt; are about consistency and context, and that &lt;strong&gt;cannot&lt;/strong&gt; be tested in isolation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You could end up with 3 or 4 fully compliant microservices, but when stuck together they&#39;re no longer compliant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Examples&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are several ways to implement microservices, but the two that seem to be the most popular are the &#39;redirect approach&#39; and the &#39;API&#39; (Application Programming Interface).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s take a more in-depth look at each one, and some of the things you&#39;ll need to consider.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The redirect approach&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this scenario, each microservice is an entirely separate application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It hosts its own front-end on its own domain, and at various points in the journey, the user is redirected from one application to another, providing them with a &lt;em&gt;supposedly&lt;/em&gt; seamless journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is often a short-sighted approach. It&#39;s an over-simplification of a complex system, which often leads to it being executed poorly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s not to say it will not work, but mistakes are usually made off the back of 3 assumptions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s assumed:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the microservice will always be used in the exact same context&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the redirects will largely go unnoticed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the user journey is always linear&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s look at these 3 assumptions and the common mistakes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Context is everything&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The context of every service is different. Not all users are the same, so if your user interface is static, it&#39;s going to cause issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, when collecting names, in a service such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/get-state-pension&quot;&gt;Get your State Pension&lt;/a&gt;, the majority of users will be from the UK. So, you&#39;re going to want to label your input fields &#39;&lt;code&gt;first name&lt;/code&gt;&#39; and &#39;&lt;code&gt;last name&lt;/code&gt;&#39; to fit with UK naming conventions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, on a service such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/apply-national-insurance-number/how-to-apply&quot;&gt;Apply for a National Insurance number&lt;/a&gt;, you&#39;re going to want to use &#39;&lt;code&gt;given names&lt;/code&gt;&#39;; and &#39;&lt;code&gt;family names&lt;/code&gt;&#39;, because it&#39;s likely that your users are not from the UK.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This guidance is outlined in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://design-system.service.gov.uk/patterns/names/&quot;&gt;GOV.UK Design Pattern for names&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you hard-code &#39;&lt;code&gt;first name&lt;/code&gt;&#39; and &#39;&lt;code&gt;last name&lt;/code&gt;&#39; labels into your microservice, it&#39;s too brittle. It&#39;s not going to cater for other cultures or nationalities where their names don&#39;t fit the UK conventions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/images/post/microservices-labels.webp&quot; alt=&quot;A side-by-side comparison of two text inputs on a HTML form. The title on the top of each reads: What is your name? The labels on one set of fields reads: first name and last name. On the other, it reads: given names and family name&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another thing to note, is if the User Researchers and Designers can&#39;t influence the user interface, you&#39;re effectively shutting down your organisations ability to do User Centred Design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You&#39;ll need to work out how to make the interface configurable, and that means taking on a lot of extra responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because you own the user interface, you will probably need to onboard any service which wants to integrate and configure it suit their needs. This is a bottleneck which causes delays and additional work for your team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alternatively, you might have to allow services to attach a configuration payload into the headers when it redirects the user, which is clunky and probably has security concerns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Transparency is good&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The majority of the WCAG issues are caused when you try to make the journey &lt;em&gt;seamless&lt;/em&gt;. It&#39;s deception that causes most of the problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When doing a &lt;em&gt;seamless&lt;/em&gt; redirect, it&#39;s only seamless to sighted users who are perhaps not giving it their full attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the page looks roughly the same, people might not notice the subtle changes. But, to a blind user, if the landmarks, menus and ordering have changed, it&#39;s not seamless at all, it&#39;s completely different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the redirect approach, the microservices are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; the same application, they&#39;re a bunch of completely separate applications stuck together. So, when you try and dupe the user into believing they are a single application, it causes confusion and can lead to lack of trust in the service as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;re up front, and you explain to the user before they&#39;re redirected that it&#39;s about to happen, quite a few of these issues will go away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;When you select &#39;continue&#39; you will be redirected to our Identity Service. Once we&#39;ve confirmed your details you can continue with your application.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Session management is hard&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest challenge you&#39;ll probably face with the redirect approach is session management. Handing off sessions and securely maintaining state across multiple applications is no easy task.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A user journey is often perceived to be linear, and in most cases they will be. But, there&#39;s a back button in the browser for a reason. People use it, and it needs to work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Depending on the design, the user might also be able to jump back to certain points of the journey. For example, they may use a &#39;change&#39; link from the &#39;&lt;a href=&quot;https://design-system.service.gov.uk/patterns/check-answers/&quot;&gt;check answers pattern&lt;/a&gt;&#39; to amend a typo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tricky part of the redirect approach is that sessions will need to be maintained and synchronised across all microservices, even when they&#39;re not currently active.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the session times out on one microservice while the user is currently active on another, during one of the hand-offs it&#39;s going to fail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assistive technology is great. But for a lot of users, it&#39;s substantially slower. You need to take this into account, or it could be impossible for them to complete the service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/images/post/microservices-timeout.webp&quot; alt=&quot;A flow diagram showing a 1 hour timeout on the initial service. It then illustrates that the user takes 25 minutes on each of the 3 microservices, so when they come back to the original application after 85 minutes the session has timed out and they need to start again.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;WCAG considerations&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;2.2.1 Timing Adjustable&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most digital services have to consider &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/making-microservices-accessible/%7Bwcagify%7D&quot;&gt;2.2.1&lt;/a&gt; due to session management. It&#39;s standard practice to time the user out after 1 hour of inactivity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your session times out in less than 20 hours, to pass this criterion the user will need to be given an opportunity to extend their session. And this must work across the end-to-end service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If at any point the end-to-end service breaks because the user was redirected to a microservice where the session has been destroyed, and they were not given the opportunity to extend it prior to this happening, it would fail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;2.4.2 Page Titled&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To pass &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/making-microservices-accessible/%7Bwcagify%7D&quot;&gt;2.4.2&lt;/a&gt;, the title needs to describe topic or purpose. It expects that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&#39;Titles identify the current location without requiring users to read or interpret page content.&#39;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one can get a bit subjective, so here are some things to consider.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The common title pattern for a GOV.UK service is:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;code&gt;H1 - Service name - GOV.UK&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A real-world example might be:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;code&gt;What is your name? - Apply for Universal Credit - GOV.UK&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This provides 3 levels of context for screen reader users. You know what the page relates to, what service you&#39;re currently on, and that it&#39;s part of GOV.UK.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, imagine there&#39;s a &lt;em&gt;&#39;seamless redirect&#39;&lt;/em&gt;, the title is now:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;code&gt;What is your address? - Verify your identity&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To a blind user, the entire context of the service is gone. They will likely have questions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What has happened?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Am I still applying for Universal Credit?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have I clicked on something by mistake?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is it a cyber-attack, and is my personal information safe?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;3.2.3 Consistent Navigation&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To pass &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/making-microservices-accessible/%7Bwcagify%7D&quot;&gt;3.2.3&lt;/a&gt;, things like navigation menus, which appear on multiple pages, need to be consistent. This means they need to be in the same place, contain the same wording, and be in the same order each time the user encounters it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Common examples are headers and footers. These are likely going to have different items in them depending on the service, but if they&#39;re not consistent across the end-to-end service, it&#39;s going to cause confusion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember, to a blind user, it could be perceived as a completely different service, even if it looks pretty much the same as the previous page to a sighted user.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/images/post/microservices-navigation.webp&quot; alt=&quot;The GOV.UK footer showing a navigation menu containing links for: Help, Privacy, Cookies, Accessibility Statement, Contact, Terms and Conditions.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;3.2.4 Consistent Identification&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To pass &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/making-microservices-accessible/%7Bwcagify%7D&quot;&gt;3.2.4&lt;/a&gt;, components which have common functionality need to be consistent across the whole service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, if the user can sign in and sign out via a component in the header, then it needs to be consistently identified on each page via its name and role.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the wording is even slightly different, or if one microservice uses a button while one uses a link, you&#39;re going to fail this criterion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/images/post/microservices-consistent-identification.webp&quot; alt=&quot;A comparison of sign out functionality on two similar looking headers. One is a link which reads: Sign out. The other is a green button which reads: Sign out.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;3.3.4 Error Prevention (Legal, Financial, Data)&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To meet &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/making-microservices-accessible/%7Bwcagify%7D&quot;&gt;3.3.4&lt;/a&gt; Users need to be able to check their answers before submitting anything which causes legal commitments or financial transactions. For example, applying for a benefit with a declaration of truth, or making a credit card payment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In most digital services, we&#39;d use the &#39;&lt;a href=&quot;https://design-system.service.gov.uk/patterns/check-answers/&quot;&gt;check answers pattern&lt;/a&gt;&#39;. But, a more rudimentary solution is to just make sure the back button works and whatever was previously answered is re-populated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, this ties in with session management. A user needs to be able to go back, review and amend any information they&#39;ve entered before the final submission. If they cannot and they&#39;re forced to start again, you&#39;d fail this criterion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The API approach&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this scenario, the microservices exist purely as back-end applications and they connect to front-end applications via endpoints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The user interacts with a relatively simple front-end. It handles the session and the routing, but when it comes to complex business logic like verifying somebodies&#39; identity, it hands over all the data and waits for the microservice to do its job, and routes the user accordingly based on the response.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/images/post/microservices-api-example.webp&quot; alt=&quot;A user flow. It lists 4 pages for: what is your name? what is your date of birth? what is your national insurance number? and success. Between the last 2 pages it routes through an API labelled: verification API.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main reason I see people resisting this approach is control. They want to own the user interface so that everything is in a tidy little silo and us pesky designers can&#39;t mess with it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To a point, this makes sense. If you do not have good design maturity in your organisation, your interfaces lack consistency and familiarity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Are APIs in scope?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;True APIs are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; usually covered by the scope of the regulations, because they do not have a user interface. They simply pass data back and forth between two or more applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, if you&#39;re the team responsible for building the microservice, if you choose to do an API there&#39;s probably very little accessibility work to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The exception to this might be if the API has an admin interface, where a user can log in and perhaps create, update or delete endpoints. In this case, then the user interface for the admin area &lt;em&gt;would&lt;/em&gt; fall under the scope of the regulations and need to be made accessible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a general &lt;i&gt;rule of thumb&lt;/i&gt;, if a user interacts directly with content rendered by the application, then it falls in-scope of the accessibility regulations. If the interactions are purely machine-to-machine and it&#39;s just passing back data and status updates, then it does not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Data, not markup&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An API should be used purely to pass back data and status updates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your API is passing back markup, such as blocks of HTML, and expecting the requesting application to simply render them out, then your API could become a single point of failure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although, if you&#39;re doing this, you probably have bigger issues to worry about than just accessibility! Most applications should automatically escape any markup that comes in like this for security purposes. You don&#39;t want any bad actors injecting a whole bunch of markup into your page!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The requesting application should have full control over the user interface. They should be able to decide which elements are right for the way they lay out the content out on the page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;re passing back markup which doesn&#39;t fit the design of the requesting application, then they&#39;re going to have to do a lot of clean-up work to make it usable for their own context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Failing gracefully&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any application using an API should not be dependent on it for its own usability or accessibility compliance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The requesting application must translate any responses and use those to present information back to the user in a clear and accessible way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, if the API is unavailable and the client application gets a 503 error, it should not just present this error to the user. Very few people actually know what a 503 error is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The application should instead do the hard work, decipher the problem, and explain it to the user in a way which makes sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/images/post/microservices-503-error.webp&quot; alt=&quot;A side-by-side comparison of two pages. One reads: HTTP error 503. The API is unavailable. The other reads: Sorry there is a problem with this service. We cannot automatically verify your bank details at the moment. You can still apply online and we will check them manually, but there may be a delay in processing your application. Do you want to continue? Yes. No&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Design patterns for the win&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The easiest way to build an accessible microservice is to build a robust API and publish good documentation and design patterns for people wanting to use it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where good design systems really shine. You can own the data, you can own the process and you can own the user interface to a point, but you don&#39;t become a bottle neck or a single point of failure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lets go back to our naming example. Your API might require the names in a certain data format.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-json&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;person&amp;quot;: {
  &amp;quot;name1&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;string&amp;quot;,
  &amp;quot;name2&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;string&amp;quot;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With good documentation on what the API expects, and a recommended design pattern showing the two fields with &#39;&lt;code&gt;first-name&lt;/code&gt;&#39; and &#39;&lt;code&gt;last-name&lt;/code&gt;&#39;, for most services they will all implement the pattern as standard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, you have your ownership of the design, you have your consistency for your user, and you have the data in the format you need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The difference is that the design is now flexible without configuration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The integrating service has full control over their own user interface, they can change the content based on their user research, and still provide the API with the data that it needs to work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Almost anything can be made accessible. But, depending on how you build your microservice will determine how much work you have to do!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The redirect approach is not necessarily a write off. If you have a small number of services and strong design maturity in your organisation, then you might not run into a lot of the problems I&#39;ve outlined in this post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m not saying there is only one way to build a microservice. APIs and design patterns are just &lt;em&gt;my&lt;/em&gt; recommended approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All I ask is you consider each of the issues I&#39;ve outlined, and really think about how they impact your users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&#39;t just commit blindly to a strategic solution that&#39;s going to lock your organisation into accessibility hell for the next 20 years. Because, as annoying as WCAG might be for you when you&#39;re building it, it&#39;s always users who truly suffer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weigh up &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; your options. Make accessibility a priority. Lead by example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for making it to the end!&lt;br /&gt;
Craig&lt;/p&gt;

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Partially supported is not supported</title>
    <link href="https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/partially-supported-is-not-supported/"/>
    <updated>2022-03-02T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/partially-supported-is-not-supported/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">
      &lt;h1&gt;Partially supported is not supported&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I usually like to write helpful blog posts. But I&#39;m going to be honest and warn you up-front that this one is definitely a rant!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s not to say it won&#39;t be helpful, but you will have to deal with my tone. I&#39;m exhausted, I&#39;m disappointed, and quite frankly, I&#39;m angry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you probably know by now, any software which is built or procured by a Public Sector Body must meet the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/TR/WCAG21/&quot;&gt;Web Content Accessibility Guidelines (WCAG) 2.1&lt;/a&gt; to the standard of AA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I&#39;m &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; tired of, is reading conformance reports from third party suppliers who are trying to push their inaccessible products for large sums of money under the guise that it is accessible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These chancers often state that some of the criteria is &#39;partially supported&#39;, &#39;supported with exceptions&#39; or any number of different ways to carefully word the fact that it does not support a particular accessibility feature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, it&#39;s not just one company, they&#39;re all doing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Twisting the truth&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lets be clear, WCAG 2.1 AA is a binary standard. You either pass all of the required criteria, or you don&#39;t. There are no grey areas. This might change with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/TR/wcag-3.0/&quot;&gt;WCAG 3.0&lt;/a&gt;, but for now, if your product does not pass a certain criterion, your product does not support that feature and it&#39;s going to cause issues for people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twisting the truth and being ambiguous confuses teams, who may not be accessibility experts, into potentially pursuing products which simply don&#39;t meet the standards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following examples are from a real conformance report I recently reviewed. The company says it &#39;is compliant with WCAG 2.1 AA with a few exceptions.&#39; Personally, I&#39;d say it fails to meet even the fundamentals outlined in WCAG 2.1 level A, given that it doesn&#39;t work with a Keyboard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;dl&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;
    1.4.4 Resize text
  &lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;
    Supported with exceptions: Some text presentation may not be preserved when resized.
  &lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;
    1.4.10 Reflow
  &lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;
      Supported with exceptions: Some content may not be preserved when reflowed.
  &lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;
    1.4.11 Non-Text Contrast
  &lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;
    Supported with exceptions: Some content may not have 3:1 contrast.
  &lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;
    2.1.1 Keyboard
  &lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;
    Supported with exceptions: Some content does not support full keyboard navigation.
  &lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;
    2.4.3 Focus Order
  &lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;
      Supported with exceptions: Some content does not fully support expected focus order.
  &lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;
      4.1.2 Name, Role, Value
  &lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;
      Supported with exceptions: Some content does not fully support name, role, value.
  &lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The status and the comments in most cases are a direct contradiction of one another. As the table is not necessarily clear, I&#39;ll outline a couple of them so you can see how ridiculous the statements are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/partially-supported-is-not-supported/%7Bwcagify%7D&quot;&gt;2.1.1 Keyboard&lt;/a&gt; states: &#39;All functionality of the content is operable through a keyboard interface...&#39; The key word here is &lt;em&gt;&#39;all&#39;&lt;/em&gt;. In the conformance report the company states that it is &#39;supported with exceptions&#39;, and then outlines how there is some content which does not work with a keyboard. If the criteria says all content needs to work, and you state some content does not work, it&#39;s a joke to say it&#39;s partially supported.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/partially-supported-is-not-supported/%7Bwcagify%7D&quot;&gt;2.4.3 Focus Order&lt;/a&gt; states: &#39;...focusable components receive focus in an order that preserves meaning and operability.&#39; In the conformance report the company states that it is &#39;supported with exceptions&#39;, and then outlines how there is some content which is not focused in the correct order. Again, if the focus is in the wrong order, you fail this criterion. You don&#39;t partially pass it because one or two things happen to be in the right order.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Be honest. Be better&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem with trying to present your product as accessible when it&#39;s clearly a lie, is not just that you put the Public Sector Body at risk, but that at the end of every interaction with a product is a person. A person trying to do a job or a task, and it&#39;s important that they&#39;re able to do that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WCAG is not a pointless checkbox-exercise. It&#39;s not even the holy-grail of accessibility, it&#39;s the absolute bare minimum you need to do to make sure your product does not exclude people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You likely don&#39;t see the effects. You don&#39;t see the people robbed of their independence. The people unable to do their job. Unable to get promoted or move teams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stop kidding yourself. If you have 10 buttons on a page, and only 6 of them work using a keyboard, your product doesn&#39;t partially support &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/partially-supported-is-not-supported/%7Bwcagify%7D&quot;&gt;2.1.1 Keyboard&lt;/a&gt;. Your product is broken! Fix it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It might seem like a good way to try and rose-tint your product so that people will buy it, but just have some integrity! Be honest about where your product is at, then make robust plans and stern commitments to make it better!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rant over, for now at least! Thanks for making it to the end.&lt;/p&gt;

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Using the language attribute to make your website accessible</title>
    <link href="https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/using-the-language-attribute-to-make-your-website-accessible/"/>
    <updated>2022-02-11T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/using-the-language-attribute-to-make-your-website-accessible/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">
      &lt;h1&gt;Using the language attribute to make your website accessible&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#39;s a couple of criteria in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/TR/WCAG21/&quot;&gt;Web Content Accessibility Guidelines&lt;/a&gt; that I see catching people out time and time again. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/WAI/WCAG21/Understanding/language-of-page.html&quot;&gt;3.1.1 Language of page&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/WAI/WCAG21/Understanding/language-of-parts.html&quot;&gt;3.1.2 Language of parts&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These two criteria are important, because they help screen readers to read out the language correctly. If your page is set to English, but some of your content is not in English, then the screen reader is just going to attempt to pronounce it in English anyway, which can lead to some pretty weird results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The HTML &#39;lang&#39; attribute is the way we tell the browser what language the content is written in. Without it, the language is set to &#39;unknown&#39;, so you must always set it, to avoid any unpredictable behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Language of page&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In most cases, you only ever need to set the language once, right at the top of your page. Any child elements will automatically inherit from their parent, so setting it on the &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;html&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; element means anything on the page will be set to that language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the following example, if we use &lt;code&gt;lang=&amp;quot;en&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt; on the &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;html&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; element, this will pass &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/WAI/WCAG21/Understanding/language-of-page.html&quot;&gt;3.1.1 Language of page&lt;/a&gt;. The body element will inherit the from the HTML element, and the paragraph element will inherit from the body element.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-html&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;html lang=&amp;quot;en&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;body&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;p&amp;gt;
      The browser will know this text is in English.
    &amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;/body&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/html&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Language of parts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;When a block of text is a different language&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/WAI/WCAG21/Understanding/language-of-parts.html&quot;&gt;3.1.2 Language of parts&lt;/a&gt; is relatively straight forward for blocks of content. You&#39;ll need to satisfy this criterion if you have more than 1 language on your page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine we wanted to use both French and English on our page. We&#39;d need to use &lt;code&gt;lang=&amp;quot;fr&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt; at some point, but we can&#39;t use it on the HTML element because the majority of the page is in English. So we need to add it to the content itself and make sure we don&#39;t accidentally wrap any English words into the element we apply it on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the following example, we need to apply the &lt;code&gt;lang=&amp;quot;fr&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt; attribute to the second paragraph, because the language is French. But we don&#39;t need to specify that the first paragraph is in English because it will continue to inherit from the HTML element.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-html&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;html lang=&amp;quot;en&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;body&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;h1&amp;gt;The main language is English&amp;lt;/h1&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;p&amp;gt;
      This text is in English
    &amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;p lang=&amp;quot;fr&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
      Ce texte est en Français
    &amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;/body&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/html&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;When there are two languages in a single block&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It can get more complicated when you want to use more than one language in a single block of text. If we applied the attribute to the paragraph element like before, the screen reader will attempt to read the entire thing in French. So, in the following example, we are applying the &lt;code&gt;lang&lt;/code&gt; attribute to part of a paragraph by wrapping it in an &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/HTML/Element/i&quot;&gt;idiomatic text element&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-html&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;html lang=&amp;quot;en&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;body&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;p&amp;gt;
      Sometimes people mix languages in a paragraph, 
      but they don&#39;t apply the correct language attributes. 
      &amp;lt;i lang=&amp;quot;fr&amp;quot;&amp;gt;Ç&#39;est la vie!&amp;lt;/i&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;/body&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/html&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Idiomatic elements vs Spans&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/HTML/Element/i&quot;&gt;idiomatic text element&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;i&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; element, often gets misunderstood. A lot of people think it stands for italic text. You&#39;d be forgiven for believing this, as when HTML was first invented that is exactly what it did mean. However, over the years, it has evolved in the spec to a have a broader meaning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In HTML5, the idiomatic text element should be used for text which is different in some way to the surrounding text. This can be an alternative voice or mood, technical terms, thoughts or inner monologues and terms from other languages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should use an idiomatic text elements rather than a &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/HTML/Element/span&quot;&gt;span element&lt;/a&gt;. Some screen readers will ignore the lang attribute on spans because they do not inherently represent anything. They are the inline equivalent of &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;div&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; elements and should only be used for styling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A complex real world example&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Government digital services, there is usually an option to switch to a Welsh version. This creates a few considerations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the English version, it needs &lt;code&gt;lang=&amp;quot;en&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt; on the HTML element, and &lt;code&gt;lang=&amp;quot;cy&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt; on the link to the Welsh version.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-html&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;html lang=&amp;quot;en&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;body&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;h1&amp;gt;This is the English site&amp;lt;/h1&amp;gt;

    &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;/switch-to-english&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
      English
    &amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;

    &amp;lt;a lang=&amp;quot;cy&amp;quot; href=&amp;quot;/switch-to-welsh&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
      Cymraeg
    &amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;/body&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/html&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, once it switches to the Welsh version, it will need &lt;code&gt;lang=&amp;quot;cy&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt; on the HTML element, and &lt;code&gt;lang=&amp;quot;en&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt; on the link to the English version. We no longer need to specify that the Welsh link is actually in Welsh, because it now inherits the Welsh language attribute from the HTML element.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-html&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;html lang=&amp;quot;cy&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;body&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;h1&amp;gt;Dyma&#39;r safle Cymraeg&amp;lt;/h1&amp;gt;

    &amp;lt;a lang=&amp;quot;en&amp;quot; href=&amp;quot;/switch-to-english&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
      English
    &amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;

    &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;/switch-to-welsh&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
      Cymraeg
    &amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;/body&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/html&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every language has it&#39;s own code for the lang attribute. To find the language you need, you can look it up under &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_ISO_639-1_codes&quot;&gt;ISO 639-1 codes&lt;/a&gt; or use a library such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npmjs.com/package/iso-language-codes&quot;&gt;ISO language codes on NPM&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whenever you&#39;re writing content, make sure you tag up anything which isn&#39;t the default language of the page. Even simple phrases that have crept into the English language, like &lt;i lang=&quot;fr&quot;&gt;déjà vu&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you do these things, you should pass the WCAG criteria for &#39;Language of Page&#39; and &#39;Language of parts&#39;.&lt;/p&gt;

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>My ADHD and me</title>
    <link href="https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/my-adhd-and-me/"/>
    <updated>2022-01-09T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/my-adhd-and-me/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">
      &lt;h1&gt;My ADHD and me&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Preface&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not a medical expert. This post is my own personal experience, where I outline some of my traits and how I managed to get a diagnosis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don&#39;t want to read the whole thing, you can skip to the section about &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/my-adhd-and-me/#how-i-got-my-adhd-diagnosis&quot;&gt;how I got my ADHD diagnosis&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also do talks about this topic, you can &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/decks/my-adhd-and-me/slides.html&quot;&gt;view the slides for &#39;My ADHD and Me&#39;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Figuring out I was different&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder.&amp;quot; I was 35 when the Psychiatrist confirmed it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I felt conflicted. I&#39;d spent years in counselling trying to figure out the inside of my own head. I thought I had a pretty good understanding of who I was. Now, I doubted if I knew myself at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I knew I had quirks. Looking at them now, some of them are textbook &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.additudemag.com/adhd-symptoms-checklist/&quot;&gt;ADHD traits&lt;/a&gt;. But I also struggle a lot with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.verywellmind.com/imposter-syndrome-and-social-anxiety-disorder-4156469&quot;&gt;Impostor Syndrome&lt;/a&gt;, Anxiety and Depression. This obviously made my ADHD difficult to diagnose because a lot of the traits can also be attributed to these &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.additudemag.com/when-its-not-just-adhd/&quot;&gt;comorbid conditions&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because of this, ADHD was not something I&#39;d ever really considered. It was actually my partner, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Eliza_Lawson&quot;&gt;Eliza&lt;/a&gt;, who first suggested that&#39;s what it could be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess, like most of society, I had a preconceived idea of what ADHD looked like; and it wasn&#39;t particularly positive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The term ADHD is flawed&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ADHD is a complex condition which most of society doesn&#39;t understand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Breaking it down into 3 negative traits doesn&#39;t do much to help. &#39;Attention Deficit&#39;, &#39;Hyperactivity&#39; and &#39;Disorder&#39; are all unflattering terms. It implies people with ADHD are abnormal, easily distracted and wayward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is likely why there is a stigma attached to ADHD. A lot of people assume we&#39;ll be running around the office, getting high on blue smarties, not doing any work and being disruptive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The term ADHD, and much of society&#39;s views, are largely derived from observations by Sir George Still in the early 1900s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still was a British Paediatrician who described some children as having &#39;an abnormal defect of moral control&#39;. He often described these children as intelligent, but went on to say they could not control their behaviour in the same way &#39;typical children&#39; could.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, Still&#39;s arguments for children having a lack of moral control and &#39;serious problems with sustained attention&#39;, appear to be entirely based on them being unable to pay attention to things which &lt;em&gt;he&lt;/em&gt; considered to be the priority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, yes, ADHD is a focus problem, but calling it a deficit of attention or suggesting people are just too hyperactive to remain focused is often misleading. This is perhaps why ADHD is so misunderstood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because it&#39;s a focus issue, it may come as a surprise that people with ADHD often have an unrivalled ability to hyperfocus. However, they cannot always utilise it on tasks which they do not find inspiring. It isn&#39;t simply a deficit of attention or being too hyperactive to focus. If anything, it&#39;s too much focus or attention to detail, just sometimes on the wrong things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the New Zealand language of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tereohapai.nz/Browse/Terms/mi-NZ&quot;&gt;Te Reo Māori&lt;/a&gt;, the word for ADHD is &#39;Aroreretini&#39; which means: &#39;attention goes to many things&#39;. In my opinion, this is a much clearer way to describe what&#39;s really going on. It acknowledges that people with ADHD &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; pay attention, but that it isn&#39;t always focused on one thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;My ADHD traits&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like a lot of conditions, ADHD is a spectrum. Everybody is different and we can have varying levels of impairment. But, we all often share common traits. The following issues are my experience of ADHD, but it&#39;s important to remember that somebody else&#39;s experience might be totally different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Organisation issues&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My personal organisation is two complete extremes. Anything which is important or expensive has a dedicated space and I know where it is at all times. This is usually a bag or a section of a drawer. Anything else just gets lost regularly and I usually have more than 1 to reduce the frustration of trying to find it when I need it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m not the kind of person who can have 1 bag. I can&#39;t just swap out the contents. If I do that I&#39;ll always lose or forget important stuff. I&#39;m the kind of person that needs multiple bags set up for a particular purpose. This way, I don&#39;t have to stress about everything I need for a particular activity, I just need to pick up the right bag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m always losing things. I&#39;m always saying to myself &#39;Argh, I literally just had it!&#39; Although sometimes, I have to admit it is pretty funny, like the time my wireless keyboard eventually turned up in the fridge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Task management and hyperfocus&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our entire work lives and personal lives revolve around setting and completing tasks. Because I fluctuate between procrastination and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.additudemag.com/understanding-adhd-hyperfocus/&quot;&gt;hyperfocus&lt;/a&gt;, managing tasks can get quite difficult.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can prioritise tasks fine on paper, but executing them in order is a challenge. I&#39;ll always gravitate towards the interesting tasks first, or accidentally work on them without realising my attention has drifted from the priority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also find additional tasks within the current task, and if it is more inspiring than the one I&#39;m currently doing, my focus unwittingly locks onto that. I sometimes snap back to reality after an hour or so of intensely working on something, only to realise it&#39;s the wrong task. There was no deficit of attention. I was laser focused! The thing I was working on was still important, it just wasn&#39;t the priority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People who do not have ADHD, or those people who George Still considered to be &#39;typical&#39;; they seem to be able to prioritise tasks, focus on 1 at a time, and complete them in order until they are all done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because I can lock onto a task and stay focused for 7 or 8 hours without distraction, I couldn&#39;t understand how I could possibly have an &#39;Attention Deficit Disorder&#39;. But, as my psychiatrist pointed out: &#39;If you spend 8 hours on a task and you forgot to eat or check in with your family, then maybe you were distracted from life.&#39;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Timekeeping and sleep patterns&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My ability to monitor or predict time is flawed. It is sometimes known as &lt;a href=&quot;https://adhdhomestead.net/time-blindness-feels/&quot;&gt;time blindness&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most animals, humans included, have a built-in biological clock known as &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Circadian_rhythm&quot;&gt;circadian rhythm&lt;/a&gt;. It gives living things a way to interpret daily cycles and provides a sense of time even if they can&#39;t read a man-made clock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, Eliza can be in a room with no windows and correctly estimate the time. She can somehow calculate how many hours and minutes have passed since the last time she knew the time accurately. And, She&#39;s rarely more than about 20 minutes out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It blows my mind. To me, it&#39;s alien. How can she just know? How can there just be a feeling that it&#39;s 4pm, and it is? I just don&#39;t have that. If I try and guess the time I&#39;m often several hours out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencealert.com/watch-the-famous-twin-paradox-of-special-relativity-explained&quot;&gt;Einstein determined that time is relative&lt;/a&gt;. It changes depending on how fast you&#39;re travelling. For my ADHD brain, this couldn&#39;t be more true! If my brain is racing, a minute can feel like an hour. If my brain is focused, an hour can feel like a minute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This lack of instinct for time means I rely heavily on routine and structure. Each day, I set around 20 alarms, and I have to make a real effort to stick to routines or I can easily end up nocturnal. If I rely on my own body clock to go to bed, my entire sleep cycle just shifts by a few hours a day until it is completely inverted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Hobbies and Interests&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I get consumed by new interests, only to suddenly find them utterly disinteresting a few weeks later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m a quick learner. I&#39;ll obsess over a new thing and develop fairly quickly up to a point, but I rarely have the focus to see any of them through to mastery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pattern is often:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Discover new thing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Become obsessed with it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Buy tools and equipment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get bored&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go back to step 3 a few times&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quit and sell everything&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wouldn&#39;t say I&#39;m entirely a &#39;Jack of all trades, and a master of none&#39;. I do stick some things out. But I certainly have a lot of skills which are not at a level to be considered either useful or impressive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Impulsivity&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Impulsivity is a particular challenge. Because it can bind itself to some of the other issues and create destructive behaviours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Studies suggest &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.healthline.com/health/mental-health/adhd-and-addiction&quot;&gt;people with ADHD are more likely to struggle with addiction&lt;/a&gt; because we appear to regulate important brain chemicals like dopamine differently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We get hooked on the highs of the dopamine hits, and insidiously justify our behaviours to ourselves to get more of them. It could be why your diet always starts on Monday, why your credit cards are always maxed out, or why going out for &#39;a few drinks&#39; always ends up with you staggering home from a rave at 7am.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These days, the two things I still consistently struggle with are junk food and impulsive purchases. It&#39;s difficult to avoid eating things and buying things. It&#39;s part of everyday life, you can&#39;t abstain, nobody will notice or stage an intervention, and the marketing barrage is both perfectly legal and relentless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Emotions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emotions can be a challenge. I struggle with highs that are too high, and lows that are too low. In the extremes I get overwhelmed and my ability to process any kind of emotion becomes impaired. It&#39;s complete numbness. Just an absolute lack of feeling for anything good or bad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In these times I can&#39;t find tears and I can&#39;t find joy. I become disinterested in hobbies and I can seem cold or robot-like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These days, thankfully, I can recognise this for what it is. Eliza is incredibly understanding, and we can just ride it out. It can last a few hours, or a few weeks, but eventually the feelings always come back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you relate to this, there is a great blog post by Stacey Turis called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.additudemag.com/emotional-numbness-adhd-adults/&quot;&gt;emotional numbness and the spectrum of ADHD feelings&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How I got my ADHD diagnosis&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Caveat&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have to again stress this is my personal journey. Other peoples experiences or advice may vary. I am not paid by or in any way affiliated with any services I recommend in this section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;NHS vs Private&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m a huge supporter of the NHS. But unfortunately, whenever I&#39;ve tried to access their mental health services, they seemed completely overwhelmed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I needed counselling, I was told the waiting list for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nhs.uk/mental-health/talking-therapies-medicine-treatments/talking-therapies-and-counselling/nhs-talking-therapies/&quot;&gt;NHS Talking Therapies&lt;/a&gt; would be more than 12 months. If I was suicidal, or what they deemed to be &#39;in crisis&#39;, it was reduced, but it was still estimated to be around 3 months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ended up getting counselling through an incredible organisation called &lt;a href=&quot;https://necounselling.org.uk/&quot;&gt;North East Counselling Services&lt;/a&gt;. It&#39;s around £45 per session, but they do sometimes have funding available to be able to offer it at a reduced cost or for free.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.anxiousminds.co.uk/&quot;&gt;Anxious Minds&lt;/a&gt; is another North East mental health service which can offer reduced price counselling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For my ADHD diagnosis, through the NHS, I would have been looking at around 15 to 24 months at least. Because it&#39;s a lengthy and expensive process, there seems to be a greater desire just to write prescriptions to treat those comorbid conditions like anxiety and depression. So, I often came away from the GP meetings with anti-depressants and anti-anxiety medications, rather than the answers I needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got my ADHD diagnosis through an organisation called &lt;a href=&quot;https://psychiatry-uk.com/&quot;&gt;Psychiatry UK&lt;/a&gt;. But, unfortunately, it looks like at this time they don&#39;t have any appointments available until October 2022. This again highlights the overwhelming need for more mental health services in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although Psychiatry UK is booked up, most Psychiatrists should be able to help privately with an ADHD diagnosis, but I will talk about some of the pitfalls I&#39;ve learned about doing it this way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;A private diagnosis is expensive&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My diagnosis cost me around £360.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, this was money well spent. I&#39;d already worked a lot of my issues out through counselling, and with my coping strategies in place, at this time, I don&#39;t feel like I need medication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, if you do need medication, it can get incredibly expensive. It will cost you around £80 in nurse fees. £25 in prescription fees. And around £150 to buy a 28 days supply of Elvanse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s not even like you can just get the diagnosis privately and then go to your GP to work out the medication and the dose. You won&#39;t be allowed on NHS dispensation until you have worked with your private physician to get the dosage correct.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I have not gone down this route, I&#39;m not sure how long it could take. But it could potentially cost hundreds if not thousands of pounds more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Life after the diagnosis&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was first diagnosed, I doubted if I knew myself at all. But now, I embrace the fact that I&#39;m a bit different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ADHD does not define me as a person. But, whether I like it or not, it is part of who I am. It always has been though. Those traits have always been there. I just understand them a bit better now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve talked a lot about the negatives, but there are many positives to ADHD which are never really discussed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ADHD can be overwhelming, erratic and destructive, but if you can tame it, sometimes it can almost feel like a super-power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The constant curiosity to learn and understand new things. The ability to completely lose yourself in the things you love. Working on things which interest you for hours without tiring. The creativity and problem solving ability of a brain which is constantly thinking at full-speed, 24 hours a day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you can harness these things, treat them with care and look after yourself, ADHD can be a gift. But if you abuse these things or burn yourself out, then ADHD is definitely a curse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m what some people might call a do&#39;er. I&#39;m passionate and I get shit done. But I don&#39;t look after myself properly. I work too many hours and I burn out regularly. So I won&#39;t pretend to have everything figured out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m still learning. Still adapting. Still trying to strategise my way around this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My new year&#39;s resolution for 2022 is to find a better work-life-balance. To stop working 10 hour days or on my days off, and to spend more time doing things I love with the people I love.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Postface&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I talk openly about my mental health issues, but I know a lot of people may not want to. If there&#39;s anything in this post which has struck a chord or you want to know more about, you can &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/abbott567&quot;&gt;message me on Twitter&lt;/a&gt;. My DM&#39;s are always open.&lt;/p&gt;

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Accessibility and font sizes</title>
    <link href="https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/accessibility-and-font-sizes/"/>
    <updated>2022-01-03T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/accessibility-and-font-sizes/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">
      &lt;h1&gt;Accessibility and font sizes&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s now 2022, and I&#39;m still seeing far too many websites using static pixel sizes for fonts. Even big hitters like Facebook do this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stop it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using the wrong units of measurement in your Cascading Style Sheets (CSS) can be a barrier for many visually impaired users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All modern browsers allow people to override the default font size in the user settings. This is part of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/TR/WAI-USERAGENT/guidelines.html#tech-configure-text-scale&quot;&gt;User Agent Accessibility Guidelines (UAAG)&lt;/a&gt;. UAAG is similar to WCAG, but it focuses on the tool being used to view the website, rather than the website itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can try it. If you&#39;re using chrome and you type &lt;code&gt;chrome://settings&lt;/code&gt; into the address bar, then search for &#39;font size&#39;, you will see that you can set it to various sizes. However, depending on the websites you&#39;re browsing, you might not actually see it work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason it might look like a broken setting on some websites is that the browser gets its initial instructions from the user settings, but it gets the rest of its intructions from the website you&#39;re viewing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The browser will always prioritise the website CSS. If it didn&#39;t, all websites would look the same. This means developers have a responsibility to code websites properly. If the website is coded badly, then it will override the useful settings in the browser and make it inaccessible for some users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The problem with pixels&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pixels are a static unit of distance. A simplified way of thinking about pixels is that 1px is equal to 1 dot on the screen you&#39;re currently using.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, they&#39;re not &lt;em&gt;truly&lt;/em&gt; static like metres or miles. There&#39;s a lot of science goes into how big a browser will actually render heights and widths in pixels. But, the important part to think about is that they are calculated based on the physical screen you&#39;re using, rather than the settings in your browser.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, if you set the font size to be 16px in your CSS, it is always going to be rendered out to the same hight on the screen. Think of it as 16 physical dots on the screen, it might slightly more or slightly less depending on the screen you&#39;re using, but it&#39;s &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; going to draw it out the &lt;em&gt;same size&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;every time&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the time of writing this, whatever you change your font size to in the browser settings will have no effect on pixel measurements, and that&#39;s where the accessibility issues occur.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The browser will literally draw the font to that static size. The same way you would draw a line the same length every time if I told you to draw it 16mm long. It&#39;s a static unit of distance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Relative font sizes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To allow the fonts and the spacing around it to scale to the user settings, you should use relative units of measurement such as REM, EM or percent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Percent does exactly what you would expect. It increases or decreases the current font size by a given percentage. So, 200% would be double the current font size. Easy, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;REM and EM are a bit more ambiguous. You&#39;d think that EM was an acronym or an abbreviation, but it is not. An EM is a unit of measurement which made sense in the old world of physical printing, but when it got ported over into the digital world, it doesn&#39;t really make sense any more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What is EM?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;re a bit of a nerd, like me, and you want to know what it means; 1em comes from the width of the capital &#39;M&#39; in traditional printing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Font size was determined by the physical size of solid metal cast letter punches. The M was typically the widest letter available in a set, and was therefore useful for measuring line heights and margins. So, if you had a line height of 1em, the gap between lines of text would be the same as the width of the letter M in that font.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m not entirely sure why the unit is &#39;EM&#39; and not just &#39;M&#39;. I imagine it was just how it happened to be transcribed when somebody eventually decided to write it down. Or maybe it&#39;s because &#39;M&#39; was already being used for metres.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess it would really mess your print up if you mistakenly made your font 1 metre high instead of 1em high!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;How does EM work?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EM, like percent, will inherit its size from its parent element. So, the EM integrates quite well in the digital world through the use of cascading styles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, if you wanted a child element to have a font size twice as large as the parent element, you can set the child to 2em.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;important&quot;&gt;
  For the purposes of this example, we will set the font size in pixels, just so it is clearer what is going on when we do the math. But, in reality, we&#39;d avoid the use of pixels all together for the reasons I have already mentioned.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Example of EM font size:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-css&quot;&gt;body { font-size: 16px; }
h1 { font-size: 2em; }
p { font-size: 1em; }
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-html&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;body&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;!-- font size of the body is set to 16px --&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;h1&amp;gt;At 2em, this heading will be 32px&amp;lt;/h1&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;p&amp;gt;At 1em, this paragraph text will be 16px&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/body&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The math:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The heading level 1: &lt;code&gt;2(em)*16(px)=32(px)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The paragraph: &lt;code&gt;1(em)*16(px)=16(px)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The problem with EM and Percent&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EM and percent suffer from a problem called compounding. Because they inherit from their parents, compounding happens when font sizes are unexpectedly calculated over multiple nested levels. The font size is recalculated with every nested child element giving you a much larger or smaller font size than originally intended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-css&quot;&gt;body { font-size: 16px; }
.parent { font-size: 1em; }
.child { font-size: 2em; }
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-html&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;body&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;!-- font size of the body is set to 16px --&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;div class=&amp;quot;parent&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
    This text would be 16px
    &amp;lt;div class=&amp;quot;child&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
      This text would be 32px, as expected
        &amp;lt;div class=&amp;quot;child&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
        This text would be 64px, not as expected
          &amp;lt;div class=&amp;quot;child&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
          This text would be 128px, definitely not as expected
        &amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/body&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The math:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The parent: &lt;code&gt;1(em)*16(px)=16(px)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The first child: &lt;code&gt;2(em)*16(px)=32(px)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The second child: &lt;code&gt;2(em)*32(px)=64(px)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The third child: &lt;code&gt;2(em)*64(px)=128(px)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get around this problem of compounding, we can use the REM unit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What is REM?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using REMs is the easiest way to make your font sizes scale and still maintain control over your whole design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;REM units are &lt;em&gt;almost&lt;/em&gt; the same as the EM unit. The key difference is that rather than inheriting their size from their parent elements, they always inherit from the root element. REM literally means &#39;Root EM&#39;, but unlike the old-school EM unit, REMs were invented purely for the digital world, to prevent the compounding issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way a REM works is by always going to the root element on the page to calculate the font size. The root element is the first element on the page, which is the &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;html&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; tag, and unless you override it in your CSS, the HTML tag will always try to inherit its default font size from the browsers user settings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In most modern browsers, the default user setting for font size is 16px. In Chrome and Edge this is labelled &#39;medium&#39;, but there are also settings for &#39;large&#39; and &#39;very large&#39;. Large is 20px, and very large is 24px. So, &lt;code&gt;font-size:1rem&lt;/code&gt; can technically be 16px, 20px or 24px high depending on the user settings in the browser. Whereas &lt;code&gt;font-size:16px&lt;/code&gt; will always be 16px.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-css&quot;&gt;/* could be 16px, 20px or 24px */
p { font-size: 1rem; }

/* could be 32px, 40px or 48px */
p { font-size: 2rem; } 

/* could be 8px, 10px or 12px */ 
p { font-size: .5rem; }

/* would only ever be 16px */
p { font-size: 16px; } 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By using REM, you can nest child elements and the font size no longer has the compounding issue:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-css&quot;&gt;.parent { font-size: 1rem; }
.child { font-size: 2rem; }
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-html&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;html&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;!-- assume the font size is set to 16px in the user settings --&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;body&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;div class=&amp;quot;parent&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
      This text would be 16px
      &amp;lt;div class=&amp;quot;child&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
        This text would be 32px, as expected
        &amp;lt;div class=&amp;quot;child&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
          This text would be 32px, as expected
          &amp;lt;div class=&amp;quot;child&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
            This text would be 32px, as expected
          &amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
        &amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;/body&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/html&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The math:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Parent: &lt;code&gt;1(rem)*16(px)=16(px)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First child: &lt;code&gt;2(rem)*16(px)=32(px)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Second child: &lt;code&gt;2(rem)*16(px)=32(px)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Third child: &lt;code&gt;2(rem)*16(px)=32(px)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&#39;t use pixels for font sizes because it removes important accessibility options people may rely on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pixel perfect websites are a fallacy. Websites should be fluid. You can never design a perfect layout for every device in the world, so just design a one which works!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may do a pixel perfect design for mobile, tablet and desktop, but are you really going to start doing designs for people browsing your website on Smart TV&#39;s, Tesla Cars and Smart Watches?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People don&#39;t care if the margin is 3px smaller than the designer wanted it to be. People care when they can&#39;t read the content because you&#39;ve locked down the font size or it overlaps when they scale it up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a general rule, just use REM for anything which needs to be flexible and may affect readability, such as font size and margins. Use percent for container widths, such as columns. And, only use EM when your design specifically needs the scaling to be relevant to the parent element. Although, I&#39;m yet to find a reason to ever use EM over REM, but maybe one exists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only ever use pixels for stylistic choices which do not need to scale, like borders and horizontal rules. Sometimes you might also want padding in pixels, depending on the design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-css&quot;&gt;.panel {
  width: 100%;
  font-size: 1rem;
  margin-top: 1.5rem;
  margin-bottom: 1.5rem;
  padding: 10px;
  border: 2px solid #000;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, finally. Always, &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt;; scale the font size up and make sure your design works before you publish it!&lt;/p&gt;

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Rising disability statistics</title>
    <link href="https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/rising-disability-statistics/"/>
    <updated>2021-11-03T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/rising-disability-statistics/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">
      &lt;h1&gt;Rising disability statistics&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The number of people in the UK living with a disability is rising.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s currently accepted that in the UK it is around 1 in 5 people, or 20%. And, from 2012 to 2019, there has been a further 3% increase in the &#39;official statistics&#39;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The number of children reported to have a disability has risen 2%, from 6% to 8%&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The number of working age adults reported to have a disability has risen 3%, from 16% to 19%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The number of adults over State Pension age reported to have a disability has risen 1%, from 45% to 46%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those are the facts. Based on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/disability-facts-and-figures/disability-facts-and-figures&quot;&gt;2011/2012 GOV.UK Disability Facts and Figures&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/government/statistics/family-resources-survey-financial-year-2019-to-2020/family-resources-survey-financial-year-2019-to-2020#disability-1&quot;&gt;2019/2020 GOV.UK Family Resources Survey&lt;/a&gt;. The rest of this post is mainly my thoughts, and definitely up for debate!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The impact of life expectancy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think we&#39;d all probably anticipate an increases in the State Pension age category as life expectancy goes up. If people are living longer, then there is more chance they will develop an impairment, and we know the likelihood of developing an impairment increases exponentially with age.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we look at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kingsfund.org.uk/publications/whats-happening-life-expectancy-england&quot;&gt;data analysis on life expectancy by The King&#39;s Fund&lt;/a&gt;, there was a subtle increase in life expectancy in the UK from 2012 to 2019, so a 1% increase in the number of people over State Pension age with a disability doesn&#39;t seem out of the ordinary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, what does seem out of the ordinary, is that the increase in the number of people with a disability was actually the lowest in the oldest age bracket. A 3% rise in working age adults, and a 2% increase in children is huge. But it isn&#39;t immediately clear exactly why.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Hidden and non-visible disabilities&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We know official statistics massively understate the number of people with disabilities. They are usually a count of people who are in receipt of a disability related benefit. But many people may have hidden or non-visible disabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A hidden disability is when somebody actively chooses not to disclose it. There are many reasons why somebody may choose not to disclose their impairments, but a big reason is often fear. Unfortunately, &lt;a href=&quot;https://abilitymagazine.com/unconscious-bias-pwds-workplace/&quot;&gt;1 in 3 people have an unconscious bias towards people with disabilities&lt;/a&gt;. This means people who are very capable are often overlooked for opportunities such as job offers and promotions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A non-visual disability is when somebody has an impairment, but it is not immediately obvious to others. Some examples of non-visual disabilities are cognitive issues like Epilepsy, Attention Deficit Hyperactive Disorder (ADHD), Autism Spectrum Disorders (ASD) or Dyslexia. Other non-visible disabilities may be autoimmune disorders such as Crohn&#39;s Disease, or even trigger specific conditions such as Chronic Post Traumatic Stress Disorder (CPTSD).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lots of sources state that &lt;a href=&quot;https://diversityq.com/dont-forget-hidden-disabilities-in-your-inclusion-drive-1514685/&quot;&gt;80% of people with a visible disability also have a non-visible one&lt;/a&gt;. I haven&#39;t tracked down the exact source of this data yet, but it seems to be widely circulated. So non-visible disabilities are definitely not uncommon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would not be unreasonable to assume that if 80% of people with a visible impairment also have a non-visible one, then a substantial amount of people will only have a non-visible disability, and are therefore not necessarily included in the data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another issue is that the support for mental health in the UK is terrible. The health services aren&#39;t equipped, and we&#39;ve been brought up with a &#39;stiff upper lip&#39; attitude to mental health which makes many people dismissive. Dismissive of their own issues, and those of others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being culturally dismissive of mental health and a lack of accessible supporting services like counselling and psychiatric evaluations means people with potentially disabling cognitive issues like depression and anxiety go unsupported.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If people have hidden, non-visible or mental health related impairments, they may go undiagnosed, unsupported and are therefore missing from the statistics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Accessibility awareness is slowly increasing. Mental health awareness is also improving. So the changes in the data could be a subtle shift in the culture. This may be giving people the confidence to disclose their impairments, get a diagnosis or get the support they need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;State Pension age increase&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An interesting point for the rise in disabilities in working age adults is that between the two publish dates of the data sets, the State Pension age has actually increased. As the likelihood of impairment goes up exponentially with age, it could be that people at the ceiling of the working age category today, would have actually been in the State Pension age category if these stats were published a few years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, people who are 65 today would be classed as working age, but in the past they would be considered State Pension age. This means we can&#39;t do a direct comparison on the data sets. Some of the 3% increase is likely to be people who are 65 and have caused some creep in the statistics of the working age category.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, it&#39;s highly unlikely that the 3% increase in the working age category is solely down to people turning 65, developing an impairment and being unable to retire. I can only speculate on it being a factor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Takeaway point&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have speculated on a few reasons why the number of people with disabilities in the UK is increasing. I&#39;d be really interested to see what other factors people think may be contributing to the rise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My experience in accessibility tells me that the increase is expected, and also that it is inevitable. The number of people with disabilities in the UK isn&#39;t necessarily going up, just that more people are actually being included in the statistics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It might seem like a good thing that more people are feeling safe to disclose their impairments, are getting diagnosed and are getting the support they need. But the sad reality is that the number of people with impairments who are not being supported is (and always has been) much higher than is reported.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess my takeaway point of this whole article, is that accessibility is not going away! If anything it will only become more relevant as the culture and the data improves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We know today that more than 1 in 5 people have a disability. That is evident from the data. We just can&#39;t point to the statistics to prove exactly how many people are impacted when things are not accessible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We all have a responsibility to make sure we are doing our best. To make sure we support everybody we can see in the data, but also support everybody we can&#39;t.&lt;/p&gt;

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Combining axe-core and PA11Y</title>
    <link href="https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/combining-axe-core-and-pa11y/"/>
    <updated>2021-09-06T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/combining-axe-core-and-pa11y/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">
      &lt;h1&gt;Combining axe-core and PA11Y&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week, I was looking at automated accessibility tools, and I published &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/axe-core-vs-pa11y&quot;&gt;a comparison between axe-core and PA11Y&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conclusion was that we shouldn&#39;t use one over the other because they both find different things. So, I set about trying to find an elegant way to use both.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve always ran &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/dequelabs/axe-core&quot;&gt;axe-core&lt;/a&gt; using &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.selenium.dev/&quot;&gt;Selenium&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://chromedriver.chromium.org/&quot;&gt;ChromeDriver&lt;/a&gt;. But this can be flaky as every time you update Chrome, your tests no longer work. Even if I&#39;m using a version manager to switch between NodeJS versions, I still hit the issue of mismatched ChromeDriver and Chrome Browser versions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pa11y.org/&quot;&gt;PA11Y&lt;/a&gt; comes neatly packaged with a headless Chrome browser using &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npmjs.com/package/puppeteer&quot;&gt;Puppeteer&lt;/a&gt;, so you don&#39;t need to setup Selenium. This makes running it in test suites like Mocha much more lightweight in terms of setup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I ran the tests for the initial comparison, it was using Selenium for axe-core and PA11Y&#39;s own headless Chrome browser together. This was fine for what I was trying to do, but it made the tests slow, and in a real project it would be super inefficient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, my initial thoughts were to decouple PA11Y from it&#39;s headless browser, and run it as part of the Selenium tests, rather than booting up 2 separate browser instances which would add seconds onto each test they could just both hit the same page when it was open.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, on closer inspection, it turns out that using both is actually far simpler than I anticipated. PA11Y has the ability to use different &#39;runners&#39; or plugins. So, using axe-core and PA11Y together is as simple as passing in the runners in as an option.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The default runner for PA11Y is HTMLCS, or HTML Code Sniffer. When you use the PA11Y API in your tests, this is the runner it will use if you give it no additional information. For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-javascript&quot;&gt;pa11y(&#39;http://localhost:3000&#39;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can see that this is the default runner, because if any issues are returned then the runner attribute will list HTMLCS. For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-json&quot;&gt;{
  &amp;quot;code&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;WCAG2AA.Principle4.Guideline4_1.4_1_2.H91.A.NoContent&amp;quot;,
  &amp;quot;type&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;error&amp;quot;,
  &amp;quot;typeCode&amp;quot;: 1,
  &amp;quot;message&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;Anchor element found with a valid href attribute, but no link content has been supplied.&amp;quot;,
  &amp;quot;context&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;&amp;lt;a href=\&amp;quot;http://www.google.com\&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&amp;quot;,
  &amp;quot;selector&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;html &amp;gt; body &amp;gt; main &amp;gt; a&amp;quot;,
  &amp;quot;runner&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;htmlcs&amp;quot;, // This attribute shows that HTMLCS found the issue
  &amp;quot;runnerExtras&amp;quot;: {}
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To run axe-core at the same time as HTMLCS, you simply need to tell PA11Y to do that. We pass in an options object and we give it an array of which runners we want to use. HTMLCS is the default runner, but if we&#39;re overriding the default then we still need to tell PA11Y to use it. For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-javascript&quot;&gt;pa11y(&#39;http://localhost:3000&#39;. { runners: [&#39;htmlcs&#39;, &#39;axe&#39;] })
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now when we check our output, we can see that both HTMLCS and axe-core found issues on the page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-json&quot;&gt;[
  {
    &amp;quot;code&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;link-name&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;type&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;error&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;typeCode&amp;quot;: 1,
    &amp;quot;message&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;Links must have discernible text (https://dequeuniversity.com/rules/axe/4.3/link-name?application=axeAPI)&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;context&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;&amp;lt;a href=\&amp;quot;http://www.google.com\&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;selector&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;html &amp;gt; body &amp;gt; main &amp;gt; a&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;runner&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;axe&amp;quot;, // Shows Axe as the runner which found the issue
    &amp;quot;runnerExtras&amp;quot;: {
      &amp;quot;description&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;Ensures links have discernible text&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;impact&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;serious&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;help&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;Links must have discernible text&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;helpUrl&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;https://dequeuniversity.com/rules/axe/4.3/link-name?application=axeAPI&amp;quot;
    }
  },
  {
    &amp;quot;code&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;WCAG2AA.Principle4.Guideline4_1.4_1_2.H91.A.NoContent&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;type&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;error&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;typeCode&amp;quot;: 1,
    &amp;quot;message&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;Anchor element found with a valid href attribute, but no link content has been supplied.&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;context&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;&amp;lt;a href=\&amp;quot;http://www.google.com\&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;selector&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;html &amp;gt; body &amp;gt; main &amp;gt; a&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;runner&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;htmlcs&amp;quot;, // Shows HTMLCS as the runner which found the issue
    &amp;quot;runnerExtras&amp;quot;: {}
  }
]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I stand by my original conclusion, that we should use both PA11Y and axe-core. But it looks like the implementation of using both is actually so easy that you&#39;d be a fool not to.&lt;/p&gt;

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Axe-core vs PA11Y</title>
    <link href="https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/axe-core-vs-pa11y/"/>
    <updated>2021-09-06T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/axe-core-vs-pa11y/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">
      &lt;h1&gt;Axe-core vs PA11Y&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We use &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npmjs.com/package/axe-core&quot;&gt;axe-core&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.deque.com/&quot;&gt;Deque&lt;/a&gt; regularly as part of acceptance tests. With &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.gitlab.com/ee/user/project/merge_requests/accessibility_testing.html&quot;&gt;GitLab&lt;/a&gt; now offering &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npmjs.com/package/pa11y&quot;&gt;PA11Y&lt;/a&gt; as part of the Continuous Integration (CI) Pipeline with zero config, I wanted to understand how it stacked up against axe-core. Can you drop axe-core for PA11Y? Can you drop PA11Y for axe-core? Should you use both?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spoiler alert, all automated tools perform poorly. This doesn&#39;t mean we shouldn&#39;t use them. But we need to remain realistic about how many errors we may still have on our pages, even if the tools can&#39;t find them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an experiment, we usually log the method, results then conclusion. But I know the results and the conclusion are the parts you probably want to know. So I&#39;ll cover those first. If you are interested, and you want to read more on the method and the details, you can read the rest of the post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to read all the raw outputs from the tests, a detailed breakdown of each test, or run the tests again for yourself, you can find &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/abbott567/axe-core-vs-pa11y&quot;&gt;the axe-core-vs-pa11y project on Github&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Summary of results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Out of 142 issues tested:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Axe-core found 39 issues (27%) in total&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PA11Y found 29 issues (20%) in total&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;19 issues (13%) were found by both tools.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;20 issues (14%) were found by axe-core but not PA11y.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;10 issues (7%) were found by PA11Y but not axe-core.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Combined, 49 issues (35%) were found.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although both tools find a lot of the same issues, some issues are found by one tool but not the other. Therefore I do not think you can favour one tool over the other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also do not think we can assume axe-core is better than PA11Y because it finds more issues, as the issues tested in this set of tests might just happen to play to axe-core&#39;s strengths. It&#39;s very likely that PA11Y might outperform axe-core on a different set of tests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is clear from the results, is that each tool definitely finds things which the other does not. Therefore, from these tests, I would recommend using both axe-core and PA11Y in your acceptance tests. By using both you can expect to find around 35% of known issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using axe-core and PA11Y together is actually really straight forward. You can &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/combining-axe-core-and-pa11y&quot;&gt;read my blog post on combining-axe-core-and-pa11y&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Method&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Testing automated tools is always going to be difficult. There are so many ways to make something inaccessible that designing a tool or a test to find everything is probably impossible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, to compare the two tools, I set up a simple test suite using Mocha and had each tool evaluate &lt;a href=&quot;https://alphagov.github.io/accessibility-tool-audit/test-cases.html&quot;&gt;the worlds least-accessible webpage&lt;/a&gt;. The page is deliberately terrible. It has 142 known accessibility issues, so it is a good benchmark to see how automated tools perform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can &lt;a href=&quot;https://accessibility.blog.gov.uk/2017/02/24/what-we-found-when-we-tested-tools-on-the-worlds-least-accessible-webpage/&quot;&gt;read more about the worlds-least accessible webpage on the GDS accessibility blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Interpreting the results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two tools do not report on issues in the exact same way. Axe-core finds issues and potential issues, PA11Y just finds issues or no issues. For the purposes of the test, if axe-core asks the user to manually check it, I&#39;m still saying it found the issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Interpreting axe-core results&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Axe-core returns an object with 3 categories. Passed, incomplete and violations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Passed is what the tool checked and found to be ok. Violations are what the tool found to be definite issues. Incomplete is when the tool could not reach a decision on whether it was ok or not. For issues in the incomplete category, the user must manually check them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-javascript&quot;&gt;{
  passed: [],     // Tests axe-core passed as non-issues
  incomplete: [], // Tests axe-core could not complete and the user must check
  violations: []  // Tests axe-core failed as accessibility issues
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Interpreting PA11Y results&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PA11Y returns an object with only 1 category which it calls issues. So unlike axe-core, PA11Y does not raise things for the user to check manually. It just finds issues, or it does not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-javascript&quot;&gt;{
  issues: [] // Tests which either failed or require a user input
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Anomalies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were a few anomalies between running these axe-core tests in 2021 and comparing them to the original 2016 GDS tests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the 2016 GDS tests, it is not clear if it was axe-core or Axe DevTools which was used. I assume it to be Axe DevTools which is a Chrome extension. However, they both use the same engine so the results should be the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the 2016 GDS tests, Axe found 43 issues in total, made up of 41 violations and 2 issues which required the user to check.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is higher than in my tests. In my 2021 tests, axe-core only found 39 issues in total, made up of 36 violations and 3 issues which required the user to check.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This could be due to different versions of the tools being used, meaning Axe itself has possibly regressed, or it is simply human error when recording the tests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Table has no table headings&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2016 Axe found the issue&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2021 axe-core does not find the issue&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2021 Axe DevTools does not find the issue&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Table that only has TH elements in it&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2016 Axe found the issue&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2021 axe-core flags it for user review&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2021 Axe DevTools flags it for user review&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Embedded audio file is missing text alternative&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2016 Axe flags it for user review&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2021 axe-core does not find the issue&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2021 Axe DevTools does not find the issue&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Link to #, invalid hypertext reference&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2016 Axe found the issue&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2021 axe-core does not find the issue&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2021 Axe DevTools does not find the issue&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Group of radio buttons not enclosed in a fieldset&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2016 Axe found the issue&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2021 axe-core does not find the issue&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2021 Axe DevTools does not find the issue&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Group of check boxes not enclosed in a fieldset&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2016 Axe found the issue&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2021 axe-core does not find the issue&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2021 Axe DevTools does not find the issue&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Two unique labels, but identical for= attributes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2016 Axe found the issue&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2021 axe-core flags it for user review&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2021 Axe DevTools flags it for user review&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>5 arguments against accessibility and why they are wrong</title>
    <link href="https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/5-arguments-against-accessibility-and-why-they-are-wrong/"/>
    <updated>2021-06-03T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/5-arguments-against-accessibility-and-why-they-are-wrong/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">
      &lt;h1&gt;5 arguments against accessibility and why they are wrong&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my role, I deal with many different teams and organisations. I also get involved in a bunch of other things on the side, just because accessibility is so misunderstood. One thing which has become quite apparent is that there are some common misconceptions regardless of which team, department or arms-length body you talk to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve pulled out 5 of the most common arguments I hear for why people think they should be exempt from doing accessibility work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The caveat for this post is that although my arguments may sound blunt at times, I don&#39;t believe that people deliberately want to exclude others. People are under pressure to deliver things, and suddenly realising that you&#39;ve not considered a huge part of it can be scary. Having to ask for more budget, more training, more staff and more time can create a lot of anxiety for people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;1. It&#39;s not citizen facing, only our staff will use it&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is probably the most common argument against making things accessible. For some reason, there is a misconception that only things which the public use need to be accessible. I&#39;m not sure why so many people think this is true, and even if it were, I&#39;m surprised by how many people think that would be acceptable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2018/952/made&quot;&gt;The Public Sector Bodies Accessibility Regulations 2018&lt;/a&gt; does not make any references to scope regarding internal or public facing products. If it&#39;s using web-technologies like HTTP protocols or running in a browser, then it&#39;s a website and it needs to comply. You can call it a digital service, a tool, a system, a portal or any other quirky name you like, but under the regulations it will be considered a website and treated like one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a weird thought process by a lot of people, that, if a person is being paid to use a product, and everyone else can use it without issues, then it doesn&#39;t really matter if it doesn&#39;t work for them. They are 1 person, they&#39;re being paid regardless, and therefore they don&#39;t really matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But whether you discriminate against 1 person, or 100 people, discrimination is still discrimination. Just because it&#39;s a small number of people, it doesn&#39;t make it any better. It&#39;s still forbidden under the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2010/15/contents&quot;&gt;Equality Act 2010&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/public-sector-equality-duty&quot;&gt;Public Sector Equality Duty 2011&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless of the law, from a moral standpoint, it&#39;s still 1 person that may not be able to do their job effectively. 1 person who does not have equal opportunities to thrive.1 person that will likely have their responsibilities removed. 1 person who will likley get moved onto other teams time and time again or have to have their work checked by other people. Whichever way you try to dress it up, it&#39;s still 1 person who is being actively discriminated against for being different; and having their self-esteem eroded in the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look at it this way. Imagine your job is to drive a bus. There&#39;s a fleet of 10 busses, and a team of 10 drivers. The bus you&#39;ve been assigned does not have a steering wheel. However, the expectations for you to do your job, hit your targets and perform like everyone else is still there. But you&#39;re only 1 person, so your needs probably don&#39;t matter, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;2. We don&#39;t have any users who use assistive technology&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&#39;Seeing the big picture&#39; is a common Civil Service skill people are assessed against at interview. But when it comes to accessibility, very few people are able to step back and see those people on the edges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The very definition of marginalised people is that they sit in the margins. They&#39;re people who never get the focus or the attention because they don&#39;t make up enough of the user-base or they don&#39;t create enough returns on the investment. They&#39;re either not seen at all or only seen in the peripheral vision of those designing and building anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By only looking at the existing users of a product, you will only ever design for the users you already have. You will never have equal representation, because the underrepresented people are never able to come into an environment which meets their needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What about those people waiting in the margins? What about the people that hate the job they&#39;re doing but it&#39;s the only system in the organisation which works for them.? What about the people who want a fresh challenge in a new team? What about the people who want to change roles entirely? What about the people that want to move up the ladder and develop their skills?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By only catering to the users you already have, you leave the marginalised people in the margins and you will create an environment where opportunities are only available to people who fit a certain description. It becomes a self-fulfilling prophecy, where uniformity is celebrated rather than diversity. If you exclude people because you can&#39;t see them, you&#39;ll never see them because they will always be excluded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;3. The supplier plans to make it accessible at some point&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This misconception seems to stem from a misunderstanding of what the regulations apply to. The regulations do not apply to the product, they apply to the organisation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sure, the product gets assessed against a standard, which at the time of writing this is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/TR/WCAG21/&quot;&gt;Web Content Accessibility Guidelines (WCAG) 2.1&lt;/a&gt;. But the legislation which enforces it is called the Public Sector Bodies Accessibility Regulations. The clue of who is responsible for meeting the regulations is kind of in the name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because the responsibility for the product being accessible falls solely on the Public Sector Body who intends to use it, they need to make sure that it is accessible &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; they use it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a private organisation makes an inaccessible product, at this moment in time, unfortunately that is not illegal. They can sell it, give it away for free or allow other companies to procure it without ever being enforced to make it accessible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, when a Public Sector Body decides they want to use that product, then it needs to be accessible. This means that the Public Sector Body either needs to procure the product and modify it themselves to meet the standards, or they need to negotiate that the private organisation does the work for them, and usually compensate them for doing so. Either way, in order for that Public Sector Body to use that software lawfully, it needs to meet the standards. If it does not, it&#39;s the Public Sector Body who breaks the law. Not the private organisation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;4. Accessibility isn&#39;t a priority right now, we&#39;re working on other features first&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of our &lt;a href=&quot;https://accessibility-manual.dwp.gov.uk/community/accessibility-principles&quot;&gt;accessibility principles&lt;/a&gt; is &#39;if it&#39;s not accessible, it&#39;s not done&#39;. For some reason, a lot of people seem to measure their successes in delivery by quantity over quality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you deliver something which is inaccessible, this creates several problems. If you&#39;re in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/service-manual/agile-delivery/how-the-beta-phase-works&quot;&gt;public beta&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/service-manual/agile-delivery/how-the-live-phase-works&quot;&gt;live phase&lt;/a&gt;, you&#39;ve likely broken the law, and regardless of what phase you&#39;re in, you&#39;ve created a bunch of technical debt you&#39;re just going to have to unpick later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trouble with accessibility is that when you find a problem, you often have to re-write the code which drives your user interface. If you find a problem with a single page or a single component at the time you are building it, fixing it isn&#39;t a huge amount of work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, if you build 10 pages and then try to do all of the testing and fixing of those at once, it suddenly seems like a huge task. Similarly, if you find a problem with a component once you&#39;ve delivered 10 features and you&#39;ve used that same component in multiple places, you now not only need to fix the problem, but also re-test everything you&#39;ve already delivered to make sure the problem isn&#39;t repeated in other parts of the application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s for this reason that accessibility is often seen as a bottleneck. Like any kind of testing, it&#39;s part of a pipeline, and the pipe only has a limited capacity depending on how much you try to push through it. Doing that accessibility work as you go is always going to be better than trying to squeeze an entire application or feature through 2 days before your release date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Releasing features which are not accessible means they are simply not done. Accessibility should always be a priority because even a Minimum Viable Product (MVP) is not viable if it doesn&#39;t work for the people that have to use it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;5. Accessibility wasn&#39;t part of the original cost, so we need to claim disproportionate burden&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The disproportionate burden clause is arguably the biggest gripe I have with the Public Sector Bodies Accessibility Regulations. My gripe is not that it exists, but that it is just casually lumped in with the rest of the important stuff, and once people read it, they lock onto that and ignore everything else. People always look for the path of least resistance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a nut-shell, disproportionate burden is a clause which says you may not have to make your product accessible if you can prove that the burden on your organisation to do so would be significant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be clear, if you&#39;re a central government department, you get millions of pounds of funding and you have thousands of employees, disproportionate burden is unlikely to ever apply to you. Disproportionate burden is for small Public Sector organisations, where the cost of a single accessibility audit might wipe out a large percentage of their budget for an entire year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You cannot use disproportionate burden as a get out clause because you have not asked for enough budget, you have not prioritised your budget allocation properly, and you have not considered accessibility for whatever reason.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can only use disproportionate burden as a get out clause once you have conducted a thorough impact assessment taking into account resources, funding, impact on your users etc. You should also get sign-off from your legal department to make sure that the burden is truly disproportionate under the definition outlined in the regulations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A disproportionate burden assessment also needs to be reviewed annually. So even after you do all that work and get legal sign off, you will still be expected to request more budget and resources to do all of the work in the next financial year. A disproportionate burden assessment does not cover the product for its entire life-cycle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to know more on why it is unlikely to ever be a good strategy in the long run, you should read this great &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lexdis.org.uk/digital-accessibility/digital-accessibility-regulations/disproportionate-burden/disproportionate-burden-thoughts/&quot;&gt;article on disproportionate burden&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Access_Rhodes&quot;&gt;George Rhodes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Defining a strategy for accessibility</title>
    <link href="https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/defining-a-strategy-for-accessibility/"/>
    <updated>2021-04-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/defining-a-strategy-for-accessibility/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">
      &lt;h1&gt;Defining a strategy for accessibility&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve been in my role for about a year now. And, to be honest, it feels like it&#39;s been about a week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coming from an Interaction Design background, it&#39;s the first time I&#39;ve had to step into a truly strategic role. I&#39;ve gone from designing services and writing HTML to designing spreadsheets and writing emails... A lot of emails.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing I&#39;ve found is that change in a large organisation can be relatively easy, and at the same time incredibly difficult. I guess, what I mean is, you can&#39;t just make it happen overnight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You use agile methodologies, you do research and you adapt. You re-prioritise if the landscape changes and you aim to deliver the most value for the current situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, agility is somewhat subjective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can all probably agree that both a chipmunk and a chimpanzee would be considered agile creatures. But their agility is not comparable. One weighs 60 grams and one weighs 60 kilograms. So, even though they&#39;re both &#39;agile&#39;, the fact that one is 1000 times bigger than the other means when they&#39;re moving between point A and point B and avoiding obstacles, the larger of the two is always going to change direction more slowly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the issue with large organisations. They often have an unrivaled ability to gather momentum quickly, but slowing down and changing direction, despite it being quick for something so large, it is still relatively slow in comparison to smaller entities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, when it comes to implementing a strategy, the process takes time, and it&#39;s important to not lose faith or give up on the journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Framing the problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before you can fix a problem, you need to understand it. This was one of the first things &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/BenHolliday&quot;&gt;Ben Holliday&lt;/a&gt; taught me when I joined Government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you know some services aren&#39;t meeting the standards, you need to do some research and really understand why.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I teamed up with the awesome &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/emmamarienicol&quot;&gt;Emma Nichol&lt;/a&gt;, a Senior User Researcher with an incredible eye for detail. We designed a survey and anaylised responses from over 200 people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The responses spanned all of the roles you&#39;d expect to see in a multidisciplinary team, plus a few others:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Product Manager&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Delivery Manager&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;User Researcher&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Content Designer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interaction Designer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Frontend Developer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Software Engineer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;QA Tester&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Performance Analyst&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Business Analyst&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Other&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were looking to discover how much people really understood the laws, their responsibilities, and what it takes to make an accessible service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We wanted to identify where the barriers or knowledge gaps were which might prevent teams from consistently delivering accessible services. We wanted to understand how we could support these teams and how we could measure accessibility compliance more accurately going forwards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you look across all of Government and a lot of the big organisations in the private sector, I think there&#39;s generally a pretty good awareness of accessibility now. Most people have at least heard of it, which is a good thing. But, the level of understanding varies massively from organisation to organisation, role to role and person to person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the scale of what it means to be accessible isn&#39;t always obvious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Accessibility... That&#39;s just, like... Screen-readers and stuff? Right?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem is, digital accessibility is hard! And, ironically, the legislation and the documentation surrounding it isn&#39;t particularly accessible. It&#39;s fragmented. It&#39;s complex. It&#39;s often written in legal jargon or it&#39;s written so subjectively it&#39;s left wide-open to interpretation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We found that generally the biggest barriers for any organisation delivering accessible services are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a poor understanding of accessibility and why it&#39;s important&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a lack of clear guidance or documentation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a lack of structured training&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;difficulty obtaining expensive tools such as JAWS and Dragon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;difficulty recruiting users who have impairments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The compliance conundrum&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We found it&#39;s common for large organisations to focus all of their efforts on the rules. All the guidance, all the processes and all the governance, they all focus on the same thing. Compliance!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s easy to see why a lot of organisations do this. On the surface, compliance is the obvious way to see the risks and measure the progress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the problem with this is you&#39;re effectively demanding people pass an exam without really teaching them the subject matter. Mandating compliance with no focus on education is an impossible task for everybody involved. It can lead to poor performance and vanity metrics. People get things wrong, cut corners or eventually they just give up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don&#39;t build the capability in house, you can pay for third party audits and you can then fix those specific problems in that moment. But, compliance is only a snap-shot in time. One iteration and your audit report is no longer comprehensive. Several iterations and it becomes almost redundant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your strategy needs to be sustainable. It needs to be built from the ground up, embedding accessibility into the very fabric of your organisation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sure, compliance is one very important part of the puzzle, but in order to be accessible you need more than that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The 3 pillars of accessibility&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remember in school we learned about the fire-triangle. Fuel, Oxygen and heat are required to make a fire burn. If you remove any of those things  from the equation, the fire will use up what it has left and eventually burn out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can think of accessibility in a large organisation in the same way. There are 3 core parts. Compliance, education, and culture. If you lack any of these 3 things over a sustained period of time, the strategy is unsustainable and your ability to consistently deliver accessible services will burn out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/images/post/a11y-strategy-3-pillars.webp&quot; alt=&quot;A venn diagram with 3 overlapping circles. The 3 circles are labelled: compliance, culture and education.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Compliance&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compliance is checking your digital service against a defined standard or law. At the time of writing this, the standard is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/TR/WCAG21/&quot;&gt;Web Content Accessibility Guidelines (WCAG) 2.1&lt;/a&gt; to the level of AA, and the main piece of legislation is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.legislation.gov.uk/uksi/2018/952/made&quot;&gt;Public Sector Bodies Accessibility Regulations 2018&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compliance is essential. Without it you have no way of measuring how good or bad something is. But, on its own, compliance is not enough. If you view accessibility as a checkbox exercise or a governance gateway then you&#39;re unlikely to have any truly accessible services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Culture&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Culture is embracing accessiblity and embedding it in everything you do as an organisation. It&#39;s the attitudes of your colleagues and the way accessibility is viewed and talked about. It&#39;s discussions, community, inclusion. It&#39;s treating accessibility as a user-need and a basic human right, rather than a list of things to check off or a governance gateway to get through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having a good culture is essential. But again, on its own, it&#39;s not enough. Being passionate about accessibility it is great, and it can be infectious, but if you do not have the right education or training in place then you have no way of implementing it successfully. So, you are unlikely to have any accessible services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Education&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Education is making sure teams have the required skills to be able to deliver accessible services. It&#39;s documentation. It&#39;s training. It&#39;s knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like the other two parts, education is essential. But, again on it&#39;s own it&#39;s not enough. You can implement training, you can give people all the skills. But if the culture is bad and people don&#39;t see the point in doing it, then you&#39;re unlikely to have any accessible services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Building a sustainable strategy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Building a strategy around culture, compliance and education, in my opinion, is the only way to ensure all the hard work you&#39;re doing now isn&#39;t for nothing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few things you can do to make sure your organisation is set up in the right way to deliver accessible services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Plan your future&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try to have a series of short term and long term goals. What are you working on now? And, what work do you expect to complete in the next 6 months? In 12 months? In 3 years? In 5 years?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you map these out, really look at everything you&#39;re working on and understand how it&#39;s contributing to compliance, culture or education. And if it&#39;s not contributing to any of those things, ask yourself whether you need to work on it at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By mapping your aspirations to a timeline and a category, you can quickly start to spot the holes. If your entire plan for the next 3 years only has things which contribute towards compliance, perhaps you need to reprioritise. You want to have high impact things in all 3 categories for each of your timed chunks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/images/post/a11y-strategy-roadmap.webp&quot; alt=&quot;A diagram of a roadmap. It has the title January to March and a collection of tasks. Each task is tagged with categories of compliance, culture and education.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Guidance and training - Education&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because we found in our research that accessibility documentation is fragmented, we decided to pull it together. We called it &lt;a href=&quot;https://accessibility-manual.dwp.gov.uk/&quot;&gt;The Accessibility Manual&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where the guidance was difficult, we explained it, and where the guidance touched on information in other places we linked to it. The idea was to pull the Service Manual, best practice, GOV.UK guidance and legislation  all into one place where people could understand it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most important parts of the manual is the fact that it breaks accessibility down into &lt;a href=&quot;https://accessibility-manual.dwp.gov.uk/guidance-for-your-job-role&quot;&gt;guidance for your job role&lt;/a&gt;, because we found that across all organisations, people are not always sure what their responsibilities are within a team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of people wrongly assume designers and developers just do the accessibility work, and that is simply not true. Everyone has a role to play, and breaking it down by job role is perhaps the most useful way we have found to help people to understand the impact they have on the accessibility of a service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We wanted to make the manual as open as possible, so feel free to use it, and if you have any suggestions or want to contribute, you can do that too! &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/dwp/accessibility-manual&quot;&gt;View the accessibility manual on github&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are also working on a series of structured training courses, which we will be able to open source so other organisations can use them once we have done pilots and refined the content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Accessibility Principles - Culture&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I collaborated with &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/htmlandbacon&quot;&gt;Colin Oakley&lt;/a&gt;, and we created 5 accessibility principles. They&#39;re really design principles with a focus on accessibility, but they complement the 10 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/guidance/government-design-principles&quot;&gt;GOV.UK Design Principles&lt;/a&gt; and allow teams to keep accessibility at the forefront of their design all times. We tried to keep them organisation agnostic, so feel free to re-use them, or edit them to make them your own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 5 principles are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inclusion is better than empathy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Accessible design is good design&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start with what works&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If it&#39;s not accessible, it&#39;s not done&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is &lt;em&gt;still&lt;/em&gt; for everyone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can read the &lt;a href=&quot;https://accessibility-manual.dwp.gov.uk/community/accessibility-principles&quot;&gt;accessibility principles&lt;/a&gt; in more detail in the Accessibility Manual.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Best practice - Compliance, culture and education&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you know the best steps to make things compliant. Document them and encourage teams to adopt them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With best practice, it&#39;s best not to make it mandatory. Every team is different so they need to remain flexible, but they&#39;re always good to use a starting point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve found the best way to do accessibility without it being a huge bottleneck at the end is to do the technical and functional testing on each page as you build it. This way when you get to the end, you only have to do usability testing on your user-journeys, rather than having all 50 WCAG criteria to check on 40 pages as well as all the assistive technology testing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;A best practice example:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Include accessibility considerations in your definition of ready on your user story or task ticket. So, before you even build the feature, you&#39;ve discussed it&#39;s components and understand any parts that might need more work such as type-aheads or dynamic content.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When you design or build any page, start with existing patterns and components in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://design-system.service.gov.uk/&quot;&gt;GOV.UK Design System&lt;/a&gt;. If you use everything to it&#39;s specifications, it should be pretty accessible right off the bat.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When you&#39;re finished building the page, use a HTML validator to catch any mistakes in your code. You can use something like the &lt;a href=&quot;https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/html%E3%82%A8%E3%83%A9%E3%83%BC%E3%83%81%E3%82%A7%E3%83%83%E3%82%AB%E3%83%BC/ohdllebchmmponnofchalfkegpjojcaf&quot;&gt;HTML Checker Chrome Extension&lt;/a&gt; or the &lt;a href=&quot;https://validator.w3.org/&quot;&gt;W3C Markup Validation Service&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Once your HTML is Valid, check your page using automated accessibility testing tools. A couple of good examples are &lt;a href=&quot;https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/axe-devtools-web-accessib/lhdoppojpmngadmnindnejefpokejbdd&quot;&gt;Axe&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/wave-evaluation-tool/jbbplnpkjmmeebjpijfedlgcdilocofh&quot;&gt;Wave&lt;/a&gt; which can be installed as Google Chrome extensions. Not all tools are the same, so use a few. They only take seconds to run. To see what each tool can find, see the &lt;a href=&quot;https://alphagov.github.io/accessibility-tool-audit/&quot;&gt;GDS accessibility tool audit&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Once the automated tools are passing, manually test your page against the 50 WCAG criteria. You can use something like the &lt;a href=&quot;https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/accessibility-insights-fo/pbjjkligggfmakdaogkfomddhfmpjeni?hl=en&quot;&gt;Accessibility Insights Chrome extension&lt;/a&gt;. If you select the assessment option, it will take you through all the manual checks for your page. It will also produce a HTML report which makes up part of your testing evidence.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Once all the automated and manual tests are passing, test your page against the functionality of different types of assistive technology. You should test it with at least one of each of the 3 main types. A screen reader, a screen magnifier and a voice controller. You should document what you tested and how it performed as part of your evidence. I&#39;ve created a few assistive technology testing templates you can use: &lt;a href=&quot;https://htmlpreview.github.io/?https://github.com/dwp/assistive-technology-templates/blob/master/html/nvda.html&quot;&gt;NVDA&lt;span class=&quot;visually-hidden&quot;&gt; testing template&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://htmlpreview.github.io/?https://github.com/dwp/assistive-technology-templates/blob/master/html/os-x-voiceover.html&quot;&gt;Voiceover&lt;span class=&quot;visually-hidden&quot;&gt; testing template&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://htmlpreview.github.io/?https://github.com/dwp/assistive-technology-templates/blob/master/html/os-x-voice-control.html&quot;&gt;Voice Control&lt;span class=&quot;visually-hidden&quot;&gt; testing template&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Once your page is passing on all of these points, you&#39;re ready to push your code. You should build automated accessibility tests into your integration pipeline as a last line of defence to stop you pushing in any obvious errors. You can implement something like &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/dequelabs/axe-core&quot;&gt;AxeCore&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pa11y/pa11y-ci&quot;&gt;Pa11y-CI&lt;/a&gt;. These should reject any code pushes if they find accessibility issues.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Now you&#39;ve pushed your page and the code is all ok, you should usability test it as part of the whole application. Use the 3 types of assistive technology testing again, but rather than using every single function on every single page, just make sure you can complete the service from the start to the end using the common features. If you&#39;ve followed the previous steps for every page, there should be no issues. But sometimes when you test something in isolation you dont pick up on things like back buttons not working as expected.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Update your accessibility statement. Now you are sure your service is compliant, you&#39;ve documented all your evidence and stored it in all the right places, make sure your accessibility statement is updated to show the dates it was last tested and the current compliance status.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Definition of done. If you&#39;ve done all of these steps, only then consider the user story or ticket finished.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Monitoring and reporting - Compliance&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without evidence, you can&#39;t measure anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Create a central repository and make sure teams are regularly contributing their evidence. In order for something to be considered compliant, as the absolute bare minimum every service should have evidence to show it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;has no fails against against any WCAG 2.1 A or AA criteria&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;works with a screen reader&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;works with a screen magnifier&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;works with voice recognition software&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;has a valid accessibility statement&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with most things, an absence of evidence is not necessarily evidence of absence. In other words, teams may have done the work but they&#39;re just sitting on their evidence. So, it may seem unfair to badge something as non-compliant if it actually is. However, if you&#39;re struggling to coordinate the evidence collection, trust me when I say the fastest way to have people bring you their missing evidence is to publish an open report marking those teams as non-compliant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Wrapping things up&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I appreciate this is a long read, but hopefully it can help you to implement some good practices in your own accessibility strategies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m not going to pretend my strategy is perfect. It&#39;s not without its challenges, but having a clear focus on improving skills, attitudes and the quality of the work is, for me, building solid foundations to deliver accessible services well into the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If anything in this post is unclear or you&#39;d like me to expand upon, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/abbott567&quot;&gt;I&#39;m on Twitter&lt;/a&gt; daily and we can pick up a conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks,
Craig&lt;/p&gt;

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Back to blogging</title>
    <link href="https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/back-to-blogging/"/>
    <updated>2021-03-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/back-to-blogging/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">
      &lt;h1&gt;Back to blogging&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, it&#39;s been a while.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I haven&#39;t published a blog post on my personal site for several years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;exact&lt;/em&gt; reason, I&#39;m actually unsure of, but I&#39;m pretty sure it&#39;s anxiety related.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve always been told that you need to be consistent if you&#39;re creating content. Whether it&#39;s daily, weekly or monthly, it should always be consistent. Same time, same day, same expectation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I guess when life gets in the way and you miss the arbitrary deadline you&#39;ve created for yourself, then what?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, for me I guess I get stressed. I feel guilty or frustrated. I then retreat from the whole process with the view of, &amp;quot;well I&#39;ve ruined it all now. So, what&#39;s the point?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This self-destructive behaviour has plagued many of the side-projects I&#39;ve started and quit. I put unrealistic expectations on myself until it removes all of the enjoyment from it and then it becomes just another job I need to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you burn out or you quit, it then becomes really difficult to get back into. What do I post about? Is it weird that I&#39;ve not posted for so long? Will people look at the dates of my posts and realise I&#39;m a bit flaky?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, all of these are just conversations which take place in my head, and it&#39;s often easier to just continue doing nothing that to come to any kind of consensus as to what I need to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve also had a career change since I last blogged. My job is now solely in accessibility. So, you can imagine my horror when I reviewed my blog which had been mothballed and found that it wasn&#39;t very accessible. That then created a bunch of additional tasks I needed to do before I could even write a post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, the development work to overhaul my website was probably just another excuse for me to avoid blogging a little longer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess what I&#39;ve learned about myself is that I often worry too much about what other people might say. The fear of putting yourself and your opinions out there when it&#39;s stuff you&#39;re passionate about is hard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, here it is. The first proper attempt in a long while of just pushing through the discomfort and pressing publish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Craig&lt;/p&gt;

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Designing the impossible makes it possible</title>
    <link href="https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/designing-the-impossible-makes-it-possible/"/>
    <updated>2018-05-02T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/designing-the-impossible-makes-it-possible/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">
      &lt;h1&gt;Designing the impossible makes it possible&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an interaction designer, I hear a sentence at least once on every project I work on. &amp;quot;We can&#39;t do that because [insert mediocre excuse here].&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of the time this is because of technology restrictions. We can&#39;t integrate with legacy systems. Or, we can, but the legacy system wants the information in a ridiculous format. So we have to change the design to ask for a mandatory middle name, where people have to write &amp;quot;none&amp;quot; in the box to progress. Urgh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s easy to make a snap decision, bow to peer pressure and change the design. After all, we don&#39;t want to waste our time designing something that&#39;s not possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only, that&#39;s exactly what we &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Design is about pushing what&#39;s possible. It&#39;s about taking something right to it&#39;s breaking point and saying, &amp;quot;ok how can we get past this.&amp;quot; If you don&#39;t, you end up designing something that is a shell of what it could have been, and probably not fit for purpose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Always ask, &amp;quot;why?&amp;quot;. Why is it not possible? Why can&#39;t we do it? Why can&#39;t we do more work to make this possible?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We should be researching prototypes that are currently impossible to build. Only then will we learn how good it could be. How easy it can be to use and how efficiently we can make it perform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Start with the perfect scenario, and then tweak it until it becomes realistic. Rather than starting with whats realistic then struggling to make it better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Government we have a saying, and that is &amp;quot;do the hard work to make it simple.&amp;quot; It&#39;s in our design principles. It&#39;s in everything we do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We shouldn&#39;t be making things complicated and difficult to use just because it&#39;s easier for us to build. Or, because we are too scared to challenge the status quo.&lt;/p&gt;

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>What is it like to use a screen reader on an inaccessible website?</title>
    <link href="https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/what-is-it-like-to-use-a-screen-reader-on-an-inaccessible-website/"/>
    <updated>2018-03-15T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/what-is-it-like-to-use-a-screen-reader-on-an-inaccessible-website/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">
      &lt;h1&gt;What is it like to use a screen reader on an inaccessible website?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Screen readers are amazing things. But they can be difficult learn and use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we see with our eyes, we see in 3 dimensions. We can look up, down, left and right, and we can look a things close to us or in the distance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Almost all websites are 2 dimensional. You can position content top to bottom and left to right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A screen reader really can only view a website in 1 dimension. It&#39;s features are linear. It removes all of the visual positioning, lines all of the content up, then it navigates through it from start to finish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can think of screen reader content as single track, you can move forwards and backwards, but the only context is now what comes before your position, and what comes after.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the page is coded up properly, there will be landmarks. This allows you jump ahead on the track to the parts you want, but it&#39;s still linear. There is no concept of left and right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another consideration with a screen reader is that the content is broken down into granular pieces and then each piece is viewed in isolation. The screen reader largely works by focusing on parts of the page and describing them to the user.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For visual users, different sections of the page can be dynamic, constantly changing or updating. If we think of something like a dashboard, a visual user can get a lot of information at once by scanning in 2 dimensions. But for screen reader users, they have to interrogate each section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can do dynamically updating content using attributes such as &lt;code&gt;aria-live&lt;/code&gt;, and screen readers will do their best to read it out, but it can quickly get verbose if things are updating all the time!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Analogies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like analogies, so lets try and outline some screen reader issues in a way which might feel more relatable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine you&#39;re in a dark and unfamiliar place. All you have is a torch, or flash-light, and it has a very tight beam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where you could usually scan the area and orientate yourself quickly, you now have to do it more systematically. Carefully inspecting each thing which gets illuminated, working out if it&#39;s important, and building up a mental picture of where you are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, lets imagine some dynamic content. Whilst you&#39;re scanning the room with the torch, there&#39;s a whole bunch of people moving the furniture around in the dark when your focus is on something else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s impossible to orientate yourself because you can&#39;t see things moving. So you need to keep going over everything time-and-time again. At some point you&#39;re probably going to walk into something!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An &lt;code&gt;aria-live&lt;/code&gt; attribute is the equivalent of somebody shouting at you from the darkness to tell you what they&#39;re doing, even if you don&#39;t currently have the torch on them to see what it is. Depending on how descriptive they are depends on how useful it is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, if they shout &#39;Hey! I&#39;m moving one of the chairs!&#39; That&#39;s not super useful if there are 12 chairs. But if they shout &#39;Hey! I&#39;m moving the chair right behind you, don&#39;t sit down!&#39; that&#39;s probably more useful!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Describing things&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Images&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We said before that a screen reader&#39;s job is to describe the to the user. If you&#39;ve ever played &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Articulate!&quot;&gt;Articulate!&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pictionary&quot;&gt;Pictionary&lt;/a&gt;, you&#39;ve probably experienced the frustration of somebody getting confused when you think the answer is obvious!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For screen reader users, a lot of interactions on websites are basically a big game of Articulate! The screen reader describes a thing, and they have to work out what it is or what to do with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For images, they all need alternative text. You can do this using the &lt;code&gt;alt&lt;/code&gt; attribute. When writing alt text, try to imagine you&#39;re on the phone trying to describe what you can see to somebody else, and include things which are important for context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m going to give you 3 examples of me describing the same image. I won&#39;t show you it, but you can build up a mental image and decide which description is the best one:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A cat.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A tabby cat.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A short haired tabby cat wearing mirrored sunglasses.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Icons&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Icons still require alternative text. But people often fall into the trap of explaining the icon rather than what it represents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://design-system.service.gov.uk/components/warning-text/&quot;&gt;GOV.UK warning text component&lt;/a&gt; uses an exclamation mark to draw your attention to the fact that the paragraph is a warning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the alt text does not describe the icon verbatim, it describes what it represents. It&#39;s not important that the user knows it&#39;s an exclamation mark, it&#39;s important they know there is a warning and they must pay attention to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-html&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;exclamation-mark-icon.webp&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;Warning!&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Always try to think about the intent. What is the purpose of the icon? Is describing what it looks like important for the context, or is describing what it represents the important information?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Interactive elements&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You need to do the same with interactive elements, like links. If you don&#39;t describe them well, the screen reader user gets stuck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Common issues with this are where people use the text &#39;read more&#39; or &#39;click here&#39; without any additional context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, going back to our unfamiliar place analogy, if you&#39;re stood in a hallway, and all the doors are labelled, you can find your way around. If all of the doors look the same, it just becomes a frustrating game of trial and error where you get lost a bunch of times until, if you&#39;re lucky, you find the right door.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Try harder&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whenever you use an image or an icon, or create a link, just spend a few moments thinking, &#39;if i read out this alt text, or this link text over a phone, would the other person understand it?&#39;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It sounds silly and obvious, but after a while it will improve the accessibility of your work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, remember not to describe the page in a way which relies on sight. Don&#39;t use content like &#39;click the red button&#39; or the &#39;use menu on the left&#39;, because this has no meaning to somebody who can&#39;t see, or a screen reader which has no concept of left and right.&lt;/p&gt;

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>One-page-applications are not accessible</title>
    <link href="https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/one-page-applications-are-not-accessible/"/>
    <updated>2018-03-14T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/one-page-applications-are-not-accessible/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">
      &lt;h1&gt;One-page-applications are not accessible&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, this maybe should have been called one-page-applications are &lt;em&gt;rarely&lt;/em&gt; accessible. Anything can be made accessible, it just takes a lot of effort, and very few people put the effort in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One-page-applications are on the rise. With them you get funky animations and cool transition effects. Some are a real beauty to behold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Building them used to be a chore. You needed a lot of &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/Guide/AJAX&quot;&gt;AJAX&lt;/a&gt; requests and complex call-back functions. You needed to manipulate the &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Glossary/DOM&quot;&gt;DOM (Document Object Model)&lt;/a&gt; a lot using &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Glossary/JavaScript&quot;&gt;Javascript&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Glossary/jQuery&quot;&gt;jQuery&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, now we can use &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/WebSockets_API&quot;&gt;WebSockets&lt;/a&gt; instead of AJAX and we can use frameworks like &lt;a href=&quot;https://angular.io/&quot;&gt;Angular&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://reactjs.org/&quot;&gt;React&lt;/a&gt;. This makes actually developing a one-page-application easier than ever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This seems like a good thing, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;So, why are one-page-applications bad?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, there&#39;s things that could hurt you unless you&#39;re clever about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most obvious place to start is a reliance on Javascript. Some users don&#39;t have it enabled. How does your app work for them?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then there&#39;s search engines. These crawl through your URLs, and you will likely have 1. So Google can&#39;t see most of your content, which will affect your visibility and your traffic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, you could be smart about this and manipulate it using &lt;code&gt;window.history&lt;/code&gt; and appending states so that the user can navigate forwards and backwards through different application states, but you need to manage it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don&#39;t, things like analytics will be difficult. You usually tie interactions to a URL which allows you to look at the data in-scope. If you only have 1 URL, you&#39;re going to have to create complex workarounds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Creating any workaround takes time and effort. If you&#39;re going to create a great experience and a great one-page-application, you&#39;re going to need a few. It will be hard. It will take sweat. Tears. Frustration. There will be bugs. There will be refactoring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All browsers have common behaviours. The back button. The forward button. The stop (or cancel) button. Keyboard focus. The caching of the scroll position. These are all thing that users have learned subconsciously by surfing thousands of websites. Your one page application must be consistent with what people know, or they won&#39;t use it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Accessibility and one-page-applications&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest problem with one-page-applications, is they often create a terrible experience for people using screen readers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With things like React, it&#39;s super easy to make a &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;span&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; clickable like a &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;button&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;, but semantic HTML is important!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is also a cognitive issue. Users have to maintain a mental image map of the page in all it&#39;s states. If they click something, and some content changes without the page reloading, they need to know something has changed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do you make them understand what they cannot see? How do you orientate this to their mental map they have been building? You can do this with &lt;code&gt;aria-live&lt;/code&gt; but it&#39;s not as easy as people might think.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Changes can be subtle or drastic. Sometimes, the whole page can change. If so, has the focus or scroll position changed? Or have you left the focus on the hidden content?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;ve loaded all your content into the DOM and hidden it, will a screen reader still read it out? If I don&#39;t use a mouse, can I still &lt;kbd&gt;tab&lt;/kbd&gt; to the hidden content? If so, your user will quickly lose context and become disorientated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you do load all your content into the DOM, will it cause performance issues? Will the initial load of the site be slow? Do you need a loading progress bar? How do you alert a screen reader to the loading time as it updates?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve seen issues where the DOM was so huge the screen reader actually became unusable. This was using &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/JAWS_(screen_reader)&quot;&gt;JAWS&lt;/a&gt;. The time between pressing a key and hearing the content was over 4 seconds. A delay of over 400ms makes any application annoying. But, a delay of more than 2 or 3 seconds makes the application unusable. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IBM&quot;&gt;IBM&lt;/a&gt; figured this out in the 80&#39;s, it&#39;s sometimes referred to as &lt;a href=&quot;https://jlelliotton.blogspot.co.uk/p/the-economic-value-of-rapid-response.html&quot;&gt;the Doherty Threshold&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don&#39;t replicate all these behaviours, it won&#39;t just be disorienting. It will make navigating your site impossible. And depending on which sector you work in, this could actually make your site illegal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, if you have to do so much extra work to make your one-page-application behave like a regular one. Why not make a regular one in the first place? Do people really want fancy transitions rather than a solid and performant experience?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People do amazing things. I don&#39;t doubt for one minute that a good accessible one-page-application is possible. But I&#39;ve not seen one yet.&lt;/p&gt;

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>What can Baloo teach us about design?</title>
    <link href="https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/what-can-baloo-teach-us-about-design/"/>
    <updated>2018-02-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/what-can-baloo-teach-us-about-design/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">
      &lt;h1&gt;What can Baloo teach us about design?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems everybody is talking about design systems at the moment. And with good reason.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mean, if you can meet the same user need with the same design more than once, it saves time and energy, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A defined pattern or component should have gone through plenty of research. So, it&#39;s also reassuring to know the design is likely to work with little effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I first started noticing reusable components on the web around 2011. Twitter&#39;s Bootstrap had a list of them: jumbotrons, alerts and button-groups to name a few.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These component are chunks of CSS, HTML and sometimes JavaScript, that go hand-in-hand, and as long as you had Bootstrap installed, it just worked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Re-usable design is not a new concept&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea of design-reuse has been around for many years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Walt Disney reused many scenes. They also reused entire characters. Cartoon creators called this re-animation. It&#39;s the process of tracing over existing frames to save time and money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may not have noticed before, but Disney&#39;s Baloo and Little John are almost identical. They were even voiced by the same person, Phil Harris.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/images/post/baloo-little-john.webp&quot; alt=&quot;An image of Baloo and Little John side by side. They are identical apart from their clothes and the colour of their fur.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I&#39;ve pointed this out, some people say they feel cheated. There&#39;s an impact on the nostalgic childhood memories of our most beloved characters. But, like identical twins, Baloo and Little John have their own loveable personalities. They may look and move the same, but they&#39;re very unique in their characters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without this re-use it would be impossible for Disney to churn out as many classic cartoons as they did, and this would arguably have made my childhood way worse!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Re-usable design in digital services&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you put one bear in the jungle and the other in Sherwood Forest, the fact they look alike becomes irrelevant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What Disney figured out, is that people fall in love with their movies because of the story. It&#39;s not just the character design. It&#39;s their personality. The script they deliver. The way they interact with their world and the other characters in it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Context is everything!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We design services, and every service is different. But, the interactions are often the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we start on a new service, we shouldn&#39;t have to waste time wondering about button colour. By reusing existing components we can spend all our time looking at the real problems. This is better for us as designers, but most importantly, it&#39;s better for the people that have to use the service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reanimating a bear gave Disney more time to focus on the stuff that&#39;s important. And we should too. This is exactly why design systems are a good idea!&lt;/p&gt;

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Mental health and flexible working hours</title>
    <link href="https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/mental-health-and-flexible-working-hours/"/>
    <updated>2018-02-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/mental-health-and-flexible-working-hours/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">
      &lt;h1&gt;Mental health and flexible working hours&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I first started working for Government, I found flexi-time awkward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until this point, my entire career had been fixed working patterns and strict start times. If I was 1 minute late, my boss would dock my wages by 15 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, it seemed alien to me to have any flexibility at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because bad organisations had conditioned me for over a decade, I thought there must be a catch. I assumed it was one of those things where people say one thing but mean another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought if I came in 30 minutes late people would act fine to my face, but there would be a secret strike against my name. If I chalked up enough strikes I&#39;d get disciplined. The last place I worked loved this secret strike system!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, this isn&#39;t true for every organisation. It was just my experience of employment to date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until recently, despite my contract saying my hours are flexible, I was still stuck on panic mode if I walked in later than 9am. Altering my world view was hard. It was one of the things my counsellor and I had to work hardest on. But now, I hold flexible working hours in very high regard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I cycle through periods of depression and hyperfocus. When I&#39;m depressed, I find it hard to get out of bed. I get agitated easy and I struggle to maintain focus for more than a few hours. I still do whats expected of me, but there is little left in the tank for anything extra.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I&#39;m hyperfocused, I find it hard to stop. In fact, I don&#39;t want to stop. I&#39;m super motivated. Enthusiastic. Laser focussed. And I barely sleep without any repercussions. I get involved in anything and everything. Can I write and deliver a talk? Can I help on another project? Can I renovate an entire room in my house?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can imagine, this doesn&#39;t work well with fixed regimes. Just because an organisation forces me to be there on time, it doesn&#39;t mean that my brain is ready to go. Sometimes when I&#39;m struggling to get out of bed, that extra half hour could be the difference between having a productive day and it being a write-off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This also works both ways. If there is no flexibility then I&#39;m going home at my finishing time. No matter how &#39;in the zone&#39; I am. No matter how good the work is I&#39;m busy doing. And, there is no guarantee that I&#39;ll hit the same flow tomorrow morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an employer, it can be a scary prospect giving people flexibility. There&#39;s a fear that people will abuse the system and that you will lose control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#39;s a flawed belief that micromanaging people gets more work done. But, from what I&#39;m seeing in Government, giving people freedom and trust inspires them to do their best work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saying flexible working hours have saved my life might seem a bit drastic. But they do give me the ability to manage my own mental health on a day to day basis, and this should not be overlooked. As a by-product, I&#39;m enjoying way more productive days and doing some of the best work I&#39;ve ever done. And that is beneficial for everybody.&lt;/p&gt;

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Validation for prototypes</title>
    <link href="https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/validation-for-prototypes/"/>
    <updated>2018-02-15T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/validation-for-prototypes/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">
      &lt;h1&gt;Validation for prototypes&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On our Slack channel, validation comes up a lot. Designers often aren&#39;t sure how to make the prototyping kit handle validation. Is it client-side? Is it server-side? How do I edit my routes file?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I made a jQuery plugin a couple of years back. It picked up a data attribute called &lt;code&gt;data-required&lt;/code&gt;. It also picked up an error message you passed into &lt;code&gt;data-error&lt;/code&gt;. Then, it checked if the input was blank or unchecked. If it was, it would append the error messages and prevent the user from submitting the form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plugin went down well. At least, it did, until the GOVUK frontend styles got updated. Since then, a dozen or so people have tried to use the plugin but found it doesn&#39;t work any more. It&#39;s been sat in my to-do list for the best part of a year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What are we actually testing?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thing is, I thought I built the plugin off the back of a user need, and I was happy when people praised my work. But in reality, I think I missed the point. As did everybody that used it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See, the plugin will throw an error if you don&#39;t fill in a text field or don&#39;t select a radio button. But what are you actually testing here? The whole point of a prototype is to go hand in hand with a given scenario so that you can learn something from it. It&#39;s an experiment, under particular conditions, from which you can draw a conclusion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we test validation, we&#39;re testing if users understand what went wrong. Whether the content in the error messages makes sense. To see whether users can fix the problem and progress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Leaving something blank is often so obvious we learn nothing from it at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What should we be testing?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we test validation, we wan&#39;t to be focussing on the difficult things. The nuances in the policy or process that might make the service behave in a way that the user isn&#39;t anticipating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;is a sort-code and an account number an impossible combination?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;does the date of birth make a claimant too old for a particular benefit?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For these scenarios, it&#39;s often easier to force the user to see the error, whether it was their fault or not. The easiest way to do this is to duplicate the page and add the errors to the second one. Hard code them into the HTML. No matter what I do on the first page, I&#39;m always going to hit the second one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can pull the information they entered into the first form, and use it to pre-populate the second. You can then their input on the field that you&#39;re testing so the error doesn&#39;t look out of place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, on the first page they entered an 8 digit account number. But on the second page you play it back 7 digits long.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, when you throw the error explaining it must be a valid account number, you can see if they understand how to fix it. It&#39;s no longer a binary blank or not blank, you&#39;re actually testing if its valid!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One caveat is; if you get a particularly thorough or suspicious user, they&#39;ll likely know they didn&#39;t make a mistake. Also, some users can get anxious if they get things wrong. So make sure you always come clean and re-assure the user once the session is over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Overcomplicating prototypes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We often over complicate prototypes. I&#39;ve been guilty of this in the past. Sometimes they end up so full of logic they are simply bad production builds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the time putting a blanket catch all on empty fields does nothing but block you from doing demos quickly. You don&#39;t learn anything from it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need to remember to build just enough of a prototype to learn about the user needs for a given scenario.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keep them simple. Keep them clean. Keep them disposable.&lt;/p&gt;

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>I&#39;ve stopped calling myself vegan</title>
    <link href="https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/i-ve-stopped-calling-myself-vegan/"/>
    <updated>2018-01-26T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/i-ve-stopped-calling-myself-vegan/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">
      &lt;h1&gt;I&#39;ve stopped calling myself vegan&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My new years resolution for 2017 was to move on from vegetarian and to become a legitimate vegan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, 12 months later, my new years resolution for 2018 is to no longer call myself a vegan at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was never a preachy vegan. I would never try and force my beliefs onto others. But if people asked me about it, I&#39;d explain why I was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My empathy for animals runs deep. If I&#39;m honest, sometimes I&#39;d rather hang out with animals than people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#39;s a certain innocence you get with animals. They&#39;re always honest!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;don&#39;t have ulterior motives&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;don&#39;t hold grudges&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;make it clear whether they want you around or not&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;are honest about their intentions at all times&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having been vegetarian for several years, I began to realise that I wasn&#39;t doing enough. I was still consuming a lot of dairy and meat substitutes like Quorn, which often contains egg. So, it seemed like by not consuming meat was I actually doing very little to reduce any suffering at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, on 1 January 2017 I gave myself the title of vegan and went about trying a little harder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my 12 months of being vegan, I&#39;ve learned that many things trip you up. Looking through the ingredients, it&#39;s not always obvious what is vegan. E-numbers are a bit of a minefield. For example, E120 is carmine, and that it&#39;s actually made from ground up insects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve also learned that I don&#39;t like militant vegans. These are people that take great pleasure in shaming people who aren&#39;t. They even give other vegans a hard time if they get it wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of the flack vegans get from the wider society comes from this small group of people creating a super negative stereotype.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, there is the blurred lines. What are the rules exactly?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have two cats, which are now 6, and I&#39;m a firm believer that adopting a pet is a lifelong commitment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cats are obligatory carnivores. If they don&#39;t eat meat they go blind and die from renal failure. So, my cats still eat fish based foods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&#39;t consume it, but I buy it. Does that mean I&#39;m not a vegan? If my partner bought the cat food out of her wages, is that a loop hole or a workaround?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another thing I&#39;ve found hard, is that empathy for people and animals can pull in both directions at once.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, I visited a relative I hadn&#39;t seen for a while. They had went to a lot of trouble to create a separate vegetarian dish for me. This will have meant almost double the effort. Preparing some things twice, and keeping everything separated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, imagine the choice I had to make when I sat down to eat and noticed the honey-roasted parsnips.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do I:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;refuse to eat the meal and keep my 100% vegan badge and make somebody feel awful&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;remove the parsnips and state that I can&#39;t eat them, because… honey? Again, probably making somebody feel awful&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;say nothing, eat it, feel guilty about it and question whether I&#39;m still allowed to badge myself a vegan or not&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;say nothing. Appreciate all the effort they have went to and accept that nothing will be perfect 100% of the time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The militant vegans would argue that number 1 is the only option. But you can&#39;t put the honey back in the hive. The exploitation is already done and the profits are already made.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;d like to say I chose number 4, but in most cases it was number 3. I wouldn&#39;t want to upset somebody who has tried their best. So instead, I would feel like a fraud. A fake vegan. Because there is a guilt that comes with the label when you slip up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I don&#39;t know if I have a label now. But that doesn&#39;t matter. I still eat 100% vegetarian and vegan where I can. I still buy soya based stuff and have milk alternatives on my cereal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not a lot has changed except I no longer:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;call myself a vegan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;beat myself up about it when I don&#39;t get it perfect&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Empathy is not always black and white. Label or no label, I&#39;m trying. And, if we all tried a little harder, maybe the militant vegans wouldn&#39;t need to be so militant!&lt;/p&gt;

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Own your Alpha</title>
    <link href="https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/own-your-alpha/"/>
    <updated>2017-11-22T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/own-your-alpha/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">
      &lt;h1&gt;Own your Alpha&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Government our digital services get assessed at each stage of their journey. From Discovery into Alpha. Alpha through Beta. And Beta into Live.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every service that ends up on &lt;a href=&quot;https://gov.uk/&quot;&gt;GOV.UK&lt;/a&gt; will have to go through this. Each one assessed against the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/service-manual/service-standard&quot;&gt;Service Standard for Government&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A panel of trained assessors will conduct the assessment. Each panel member from a different discipline within digital. The panel will cover the team setup. Their design and research, and their chosen technology stack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From my time as an assessor, I&#39;ve noticed teams don&#39;t always conduct Alphas correctly. It&#39;s not that the team setup is wrong. It&#39;s also not their ways of working. They work in an iterative manner and use agile methodologies well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;So, what&#39;s the problem?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, what I often see in Alpha assessments, is that teams aren&#39;t striving to find the right solution. They have a first attempt. They then continue to tweak the design. And, by the end of the Alpha they have something they can take into Beta.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem with this, is that you&#39;ve conducted a Beta during your Alpha phase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have worked in an iterative manner. But, you&#39;ve only iterated parts of the same design. You&#39;re missing huge opportunities to find the very best solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sure, your design might be ok. It might do ok in research sessions. But you can&#39;t be sure it&#39;s the right solution if it&#39;s the only one you&#39;ve tried.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a general observation, humans often don&#39;t get things right first time. Experience can get you close, but it&#39;s still unlikely you will get it perfect. And this is why the Alpha phase is amazing for designers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, as a designer, the Alpha phase is the best part. It&#39;s a clean slate. Blue sky thinking. It&#39;s the part where I can pull everything apart and ask challenging questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why can&#39;t we do that? Why should the design fit the existing crappy process? Why aren&#39;t we changing the crappy process? Why don&#39;t we do something completely different instead? What can you hook into in the back-end to make this less tedious for users?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alpha is the phase where I do most of my design work. Where I get it wrong, a lot! But I also learn the most. It&#39;s about huge iterations. Completely different design approaches. Alternate user journeys. And if it doesn&#39;t work? Tear the whole thing up and start again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be bold. Iterate wildly. Then, sit in front of the panel and tell them with no doubts how you know that you&#39;ve designed the best solution.&lt;/p&gt;

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Semantics and accessibility</title>
    <link href="https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/semantics-and-accessibility/"/>
    <updated>2017-10-10T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/semantics-and-accessibility/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">
      &lt;h1&gt;Semantics and accessibility&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used to think semantic HTML was only about getting that little W3C badge on your website. I thought it was bragging rights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the past, I&#39;ve been guilty of using &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;div&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; elements for pretty much everything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve also been guilty of changing a &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;h1&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; element to a &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;h2&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; element because I needed it to look smaller.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As designers, we always like to put our stamp on things. We like to make things fancy and show off our full range of talents. Then when it comes to coding them up, we abuse our design!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We float things right. We use absolute positioning. We style links to look like buttons. We use fancy hover states and chuck in break tags in to create whitespace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, we marvel at how pretty our designs look. After all, as long as it looks good, that&#39;s all that matters. Right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, not exactly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why semantics is important&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By making things pretty first and correct second, we make a major mistake. We assume that everybody navigates the web the same way. With a mouse. With no colour correction. With 20/20 vision. But, this couldn&#39;t be further from the truth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#39;s a common misconception that people using assistive technologies are an edge case. That they fall into that 1% with those that disable Javascript. But that isn&#39;t true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my last &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.craigabbott.co.uk/accessibility-is-not-an-edge-case&quot;&gt;blog post: &#39;Accessibility is not an edge case&#39;&lt;/a&gt; I did some research. I found in the UK alone, the current statistics indicate that around 9.3 million people living with a disability use the internet regularly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of people think accessibility is all about using &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/WAI/intro/aria&quot;&gt;WAI-ARIA&lt;/a&gt;. But, when it comes to your markup, using the correct syntax gets you a lot of accessibility for free. Having the correct tags. The correct heading levels and the correct hierarchy on the page will give you a huge head start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/nonswearyphil&quot;&gt;Phil Sherry&lt;/a&gt; says, don&#39;t code for &#39;mobile first&#39;, code for &#39;screen-reader first&#39;. Removing all the CSS and JavaScript should leave something that is still coherent. Then add all the fancy stuff after.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We should be designing accessible websites because it&#39;s the right thing to do. But even as a business case, there&#39;s a potential 9.3 million people that can&#39;t use your service or buy your products.&lt;/p&gt;

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Accessibility is not an edge case</title>
    <link href="https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/accessibility-is-not-an-edge-case/"/>
    <updated>2017-09-27T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/accessibility-is-not-an-edge-case/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">
      &lt;h1&gt;Accessibility is not an edge case&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#39;s a common misconception that people using assistive technologies are an edge case. That they fall into that 1% where people disable Javascript. But, this couldn&#39;t be further from the truth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m going to show you why it&#39;s important to make your website accessible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few disclaimers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m combining figures from reports in 2014, 2016 and 2017. So the results won&#39;t be representative of a single historic year. Instead, they will be the most up to date figures I could find.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reports will only capture those with a diagnosis. Those in receipt of a disability related benefit. Or, those who took part in research by the Office for National Statistics. It&#39;s likely there are more people who have disabilities but are not included in the data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of those people with a disability who do use the internet, not all will need to use assistive technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m only using UK statistics. People can access websites from anywhere in the world, so the figures will actually be far higher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Lets do some math&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year, 65,648,054 lived in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of these, 63% were aged 16-64, and 18% were over 65. Combined, this is around 53.2 million adults.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working out:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-less&quot;&gt;63% of 65,648,054 = 41,358,274
18% of 65,648,054 = 11,816,649
41,358,274 + 11,816,649 = 53,174,923
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2014, 16% of working age people and 45% of people over state pension age were living with a disability. Combined, that&#39;s 11.9 million people in the UK alone. Around 1 in 5, or 20%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working out:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-less&quot;&gt;16% of 41,358,274 = 6,617,323
45% of 11,816,649 = 5,317,492
6,617,323 + 5,317,492 = 11,934,815
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, in 2017, only 22% of adults living with a disability said they had never used the internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, of our 11.9 million people, we can remove 22% This leaves us with the number people living with a disability that do use the internet. Which is 9.3 million.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working out:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-less&quot;&gt;22% of 11,934,815 = 2,625,659
11,934,815 - 2,625,659 = 9,309,155
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is almost 10 million people in the UK alone are surfing the web with a disability. &lt;em&gt;Definitely NOT an edge case.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing I have seen repeatedly from research, is that people always find a way to do things. People are amazing, and will learn and adapt. Those with visual impairments may use screen readers. Those with motor impairments may use a keyboard or voice activation software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have no way of detecting these devices. So, as designers and developers, it is important we design with these people in mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having semantic markup, correct tab indexes and accessible content has never been more important. And by making our websites work better for these people, we will automatically make it better for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Citations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/disability-facts-and-figures/disability-facts-and-figures&quot;&gt;Disability facts and figures 2014 - gov.uk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ons.gov.uk/peoplepopulationandcommunity/populationandmigration/populationestimates/articles/overviewoftheukpopulation/july2017&quot;&gt;Overview of UK population 2017 - Office for National Statistics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ons.gov.uk/businessindustryandtrade/itandinternetindustry/bulletins/internetusers/2017&quot;&gt;IT and internet users 2017 - Office for National Statistics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://webaim.org/projects/screenreadersurvey6/&quot;&gt;Screen reader survey 2015 - WebAim&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.papworthtrust.org.uk/sites/default/files/Disability%20Facts%20and%20Figures%202016.pdf&quot;&gt;Disability facts and figures 2016 - Papworth Trust&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Bug fixes and performance improvements</title>
    <link href="https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/bug-fixes-and-performance-improvements/"/>
    <updated>2017-08-22T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/bug-fixes-and-performance-improvements/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">
      &lt;h1&gt;Bug fixes and performance improvements&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On my iPhone, I don&#39;t have automatic updates turned on. I&#39;m that guy that likes to read the release notes. Or, at least, I was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Release notes used to be interesting. They&#39;d tell you what the developers had been up to. What features they were adding, or removing. But, the most important thing they brought was the ability to make an informed decision. They gave you the chance to decide whether you actually wanted to install it or not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Companies such as Slack and Monzo have fun with their release notes. They&#39;re proud to show you the new features they&#39;ve been working hard on. But these two companies are becoming part of a minority. A small group of companies that actually bother to write anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, the App Store is full of lazy release notes, and this is a huge disservice to users. The most alarming thing is the tech giants that should be leading by example are the worst offenders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some examples:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;dl&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;
    Facebook
  &lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;
    Thanks for using Facebook! To make our app better for you, we bring updates to the App Store regularly. Every update of our Facebook app includes improvements for speed and reliability. As new features become available, we&#39;ll highlight those for you in the app.
  &lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;
    Instagram
  &lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;
    Bug fixes and performance improvements.
  &lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;
    Twitter
  &lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;
    A few minor updates to make twitter an even better place.
  &lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;
    WhatsApp
  &lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;
    Bug fixes.
  &lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;
    Spotify
  &lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;
    We&#39;re always making changes and improving Spotify. To make sure you don&#39;t miss a thing, just keep your updates turned on.
  &lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;
    YouTube
  &lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;
    Fixed bugs, improved performance and included a compatibility update just for you.
  &lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;
    Netflix
  &lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;
    Bug fixes.
  &lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;
  &lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;
  &lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;
  &lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;
  &lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;
    Google Drive
  &lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;
    Performance improvements and bug fixes.
  &lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;
    Gmail
  &lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;
    Bug fixes and performance improvements.
  &lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;
    LinkedIn
  &lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;
    General bug fixes and performance improvements.
  &lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;
    Kindle
  &lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;
    Bug fixes and performance improvements.
  &lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From those examples, I can&#39;t see a single piece of information that&#39;s useful. They could have added anything to the app and I&#39;d have no way of knowing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thing is, we know companies like Facebook are not always ethical. We know a huge amount of their revenue comes from tracking and data gathering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, when companies like this are rolling out updates every other week, it makes you wonder what they&#39;ve been up to. How much stuff are they sneaking in under the hood that you might not sign up to given the choice?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the iPhone, there&#39;s a setting that allows apps to update themselves as soon as there&#39;s one available. Because of this, you could argue that nobody reads the release notes anyway. Why waste an hour of a developers time to write a few bullet points? Right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem with this way of thinking is that it excludes the people that &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; read them. When it comes to release notes you only have two user groups. Those that read them, and those that don&#39;t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As designers and developers, we need to always be designing for the edge case. In doing so we will make the experience better for everybody.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also means you cannot say you&#39;re being transparent and working in the open.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you create software that people install on their devices, at least have the decency to tell them what it does. The only reason not to be transparent is if you&#39;re doing something sinister. And if this is the case, your users should have the right to opt out.&lt;/p&gt;

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Design is not art</title>
    <link href="https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/design-is-not-art/"/>
    <updated>2017-08-16T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/design-is-not-art/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">
      &lt;h1&gt;Design is not art&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Design and art go hand in hand. But they&#39;re not the same thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was younger, I identified as a graphic designer. I&#39;d design logos and flyers for nightclubs in Newcastle. When you&#39;re doing this kind of thing, the lines between art and design blur a lot. And, I have to be honest, I didn&#39;t know the difference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;d combine art with principles such as the golden ratio, irradiation phenomenon and overshoot. I&#39;d pick typefaces to best represent the brand of the company I was designing for. There was some science to it, but it was still open to opinion. Somebody could still decide they didn&#39;t like my work. And clients often did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Art is to be enjoyed&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Art is meant to inspire those that connect with it. But, by that logic, not everyone &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; connect with it. This makes art subjective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can&#39;t gather evidence to prove that art is good or bad, and even famous artwork with legendary status could be viewed as terrible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remember in school, telling my teacher Pablo Picasso was rubbish. She was furious, but this was my opinion. If you don&#39;t like something, you just don&#39;t like it. And you can&#39;t argue with somebody&#39;s opinion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Design is different&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose of a design is to be interacted with so that somebody can do something. For example. a door, a website, or a car.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you design something badly, people notice. And, if you design something well, people should never know you were there. A bad design can disable somebody from completing a task. But the good thing about this, is that you can &lt;em&gt;prove&lt;/em&gt; when it&#39;s bad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, a door you have to push to open that has a pull handle. These always catch me out. You can tell it&#39;s a bad design by observing people using it. If 10 people go through it, and 9 of them try to pull it, then your design is bad. You can&#39;t argue with the observed evidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As designers, it&#39;s important that we always consider this. It&#39;s important that we don&#39;t just design things that we think are pretty. Sure, good design should have some aesthetics to it. Anybody that&#39;s held any Apple product will know how good it feels in your hands. But all too often, the usability is sacrificed for aesthetics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&#39;re in the unique position where we design things that make a difference to peoples lives. It&#39;s important to make sure that we research often. That we do the hard work to make it simple for those that use our products.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make your door ugly, or make it pretty. But make damn sure it works!&lt;/p&gt;

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Death of the notes box</title>
    <link href="https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/death-of-the-notes-box/"/>
    <updated>2017-08-14T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/death-of-the-notes-box/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">
      &lt;h1&gt;Death of the notes box&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a designer, it&#39;s not my job to design the things people &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt;. It&#39;s my job to design the things they &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you work in Government, you see a lot of legacy systems. These are ancient beasts, built off the back of corporate I.T contracts decades ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They&#39;re clunky, and we&#39;re unable to make changes. UX wasn&#39;t even a thing back then. The interfaces range from what looks like Teletext to an Excel spreadsheet. The font size is about 6px, because any screen resolution over 640px was unheard of when they were built.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#39;s a lot these systems have to answer for. But one of my biggest gripes is the culture of &#39;note-box enthusiasts&#39; these systems have created.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The notes box has become a global dumping ground for anything the user thinks &#39;might&#39; be useful. Whether they&#39;re processing an application or dealing with a customer query, they just fill the notes box with lines and lines of redundant information. Just in case there&#39;s a slight chance somebody else might need it in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some people think they&#39;re being helpful. Should anybody else want that information, it&#39;s there. Others do it out of fear. They&#39;re covering their own back, proving they&#39;re being thorough with their work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Customer rang at 14:06 to change bank details. Updated account number from 12345678 to 87654321 and sort-code from 12-34-56 to 65-43-21.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This might look helpful, but it highlights how the notes box can be a security minefield!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should always encrypt passwords, bank account details and other sensitive information. This is obvious. But, what is often overlooked, is that the notes field is not always encrypted. So, the above note would store bank details as plain text. Whilst this is a hypothetical example, it shows how you can expose information through human error. And this puts customer data and your users at risk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a designer, we should be thinking long and hard about how we design services. Having worked on an admin system for the past 12 months, removing the notes box has been a challenge. But, we managed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&#39;ve replaced notes with a logging system. It captures the key information at trigger points in the journey, and creates the notes for you. This way all the need-to-know information is there, and all the redundant stuff is gone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It sounds simple. And it is. But it&#39;s been a long hard fight. This is because it goes against what the user &lt;em&gt;wants&lt;/em&gt; and instead only provides them with what they &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need to do the hard work to make it simple. As designers, we need to make sure we always challenge the status quo and design for user needs. But at the same time, we need to make sure we build trust and rapport with users through regular user research. This will allow us to understand user needs and come to the right design decisions together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As always, I&#39;m happy to discuss this further. Just get in touch.&lt;/p&gt;

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Error messages are not funny</title>
    <link href="https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/error-messages-are-not-funny/"/>
    <updated>2017-08-07T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/error-messages-are-not-funny/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">
      &lt;h1&gt;Error messages are not funny&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m at that age now where all my friends are into having babies. Because of this, I ended up browsing &lt;a href=&quot;http://kidly.co.uk/&quot;&gt;kidly.co.uk&lt;/a&gt;. It&#39;s an eCommerce site aimed at gifts for children between 0 and 4 years old.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They do a great job of selling themselves as a &#39;by people for people&#39; kind of company. There are fluffy images of the team looking happy. The about us section is full of references to parenting so that people can relate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I get this type of marketing. It&#39;s smart. It bypasses your brain&#39;s neocortex and buries itself deep into your emotional core. If you relate to these people, and they seem like you, you&#39;re more likely to buy from them. It&#39;s genius!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&#39;t have a problem with this type of marketing, until it begins to encroach on the user experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the page that asked for my details, I hit the submit button on the form without entering my phone number. I was then faced with the following red validation error, placed below the field I had left out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oops, you forgot to pop in your number! Don&#39;t be shy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are so many things wrong with this error message, and it caused a bit of a debate when I tweeted about it. You can &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/abbott567/status/867654758588440576&quot;&gt;read the debate on error messages on twitter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Out of curiosity, I deleted everything and hit submit again to see the full extent of the problem. The following screenshot shows the error messages in all their glory. For the sake of this post, I&#39;m going to focus on the mobile number field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/images/post/error-messages-are-not-funny.webp&quot; alt=&quot;A screenshot of kidly.co.uk&#39;s website. It shows 3 text fields for recipient name, your mobile and recipient address. The error messages read: Please enter a recipient name. Oops, you forgot to pop in your mobile number, don&#39;t be shy. And, Doh! We need this to know where we&#39;re going.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Making assumptions about behaviour&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It suggests I forgot to enter my number. But, I didn&#39;t &lt;em&gt;forget&lt;/em&gt;. I deliberately didn&#39;t enter my phone number, because I didn&#39;t want to. Particularly because buried in the privacy policy you can find the phrase:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From time to time, we may also use your information to contact you for market research purposes. We may contact you by email, phone, fax or mail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What if I didn&#39;t own a mobile phone? What if I couldn&#39;t remember my number? By making this field mandatory, they were already excluding a set of users. They&#39;re saying, &#39;If you don&#39;t give us a phone number to spam you with, you can&#39;t buy this stuff you wanted.&#39;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;re truly doing user centred design, only ask for information that is essential. By forcing people to enter a mobile number for marketing purposes, you are designing for the needs of the business. This will make people drop out before paying you any money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A solution is to not ask for the mobile number, or at the very least make it optional and tell the user exactly why you want it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Assuming personality&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&#39;Don&#39;t be shy.&#39; Well, this is a bit insulting. I wasn&#39;t shy. I was trying to pay for my stuff! We&#39;re not on a first date. I&#39;m not even using Tinder. It&#39;s a website, where you offer products and I buy the ones I want. Making assumptions about peoples reasons for omitting something is an absolute minefield.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A solution here would be to delete this immediately. Then, have a quiet word with yourself for thinking it was a good idea in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Using idioms&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pop&#39; in your number? How do you &#39;pop in&#39; a number? This type of language is known as an idiom. It means you have no way of working out what it means without anybody teaching you explicitly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This type of language can lead to difficulties. It is particularly difficult for people who speak English as a second language, and autistic people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Autistic people can take things quite literally. Phrases such as &#39;Over the moon&#39; and &#39;raining cats and dogs&#39; can be confusing and stressful. It places them under unnecessary cognitive load.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A better solution is to tell the user exactly what they need to do to progress. If you need a phone number and there is no way round it, then explain that. The phrase &#39;enter a phone number&#39; leaves no ambiguity as to what the user needs to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Humour&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The language tries to sound light hearted. It&#39;s trying to be amusing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the twitter debate, somebody asked the following question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&#39;Do you wonder if it breaks the user&#39;s frustration and makes them chuckle?&#39;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No. I don&#39;t think it does. I have no user need to be entertained. I have no user need for a chuckle during the checkout process. My need at this point is still very much to buy a gift for my friend&#39;s baby. And if I don&#39;t understand what the error message is telling me, it&#39;s going to make the process even more frustrating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The solution to this again is to tell the user exactly what they need to do to progress, using as few words as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Inaccessible markup&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They have positioned the message telling you what is wrong below the field. Imagine you can&#39;t see the screen and you&#39;re using a screen reader. You will have to navigate past the thing you need to fix to find out what you did wrong. Then, you have to go back up the page again to edit the field, and this can be disorientating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The solution to this is to inform the user there has been a problem. Then to give a summary to what they need to do to fix it along with clear and concise error messages on each field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m going to base the next example on the design pattern we use for errors and validation in Government. You can &lt;a href=&quot;https://design-system.service.gov.uk/patterns/validation/&quot;&gt;view the GOV.UK design pattern for helping users to recover from validation errors&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First thing to do is to state an error has occurred in the page title. For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-html&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;title&amp;gt;Error: Your details&amp;lt;/title&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, add an error container with a good heading. This can be something like &#39;There is a problem.&#39; It should be the first thing in the main tag on the page. This lets the screen reader users orientate themselves quickly once the page has reloaded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Add &lt;code&gt;role=&amp;quot;alert&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt; to the container and add a tab index of -1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using &lt;code&gt;role=&amp;quot;alert&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt; will make the screen reader announce it as soon as it&#39;s rendered on the page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tabindex allows you to fire some JavaScript when the document has loaded to set the focus to the error summary. This ensures that the user can navigate through the errors easily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By default, only links and form elements are focusable. But, adding a tab index of -1 allows you to focus it them using JavaScript. Because it&#39;s -1, and not 0 or higher. it wont add it to the usual flow of links and form elements that happens when you hit the &lt;kbd&gt;tab&lt;/kbd&gt; key.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-html&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div id=&amp;quot;error-summary&amp;quot; role=&amp;quot;alert&amp;quot; tabindex=&amp;quot;-1&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;h1&amp;gt;There&#39;s been a problem&amp;lt;/h1&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-javascript&quot;&gt;document.addEventListener(&amp;quot;DOMContentLoaded&amp;quot;, () =&amp;gt; { 
  document.querySelector(&#39;#error-summary&#39;).focus()
})
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, add a list of the errors in the summary. This helps the user understand how many issues there are and how to fix each one before they even attempt to navigate the page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-html&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div id=&amp;quot;error-summary&amp;quot; tabindex=&amp;quot;-1&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;h1&amp;gt;There&#39;s been a problem&amp;lt;/h1&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Check the following:&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;ul&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;li&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;a href=&amp;quot;#mobile-number&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
        Mobile number cannot be blank
      &amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;/ul&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last but not least. Position your error messages between the label and the input instead of underneath. This gives it a more natural flow and means the user does not have to navigate past the input to find out what&#39;s wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can then link it to the input using &lt;code&gt;aria-describedby&lt;/code&gt; to make sure the additional context is read out by screen readers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-html&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div class=&amp;quot;form-group form-group--error&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;label for=&amp;quot;mobile-number&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
    Mobile number
  &amp;lt;/label&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;p id=&amp;quot;mobile-number-error&amp;quot; class=&amp;quot;error-message&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
   Error: Enter your mobile number
  &amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;input class=&amp;quot;input--error&amp;quot; id=&amp;quot;mobile-number&amp;quot; type=&amp;quot;text&amp;quot; aria-describedby=&amp;quot;mobile-number-error&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, when the page loads, the screen reader will automatically focus the error summary. Read out there&#39;s been a problem. Give you a list the problems in a concise manner, and link each list item to the input.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As always, I&#39;m happy to discussing anything I&#39;ve written about in more detail, just get in touch.&lt;/p&gt;

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Some thoughts on primary buttons</title>
    <link href="https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/some-thoughts-on-primary-buttons/"/>
    <updated>2017-07-26T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/some-thoughts-on-primary-buttons/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">
      &lt;h1&gt;Some thoughts on primary buttons&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve recently been ranting a lot about primary buttons. But people often don&#39;t understand what they are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my early days as a designer, I thought it just meant adding &lt;code&gt;class=&amp;quot;btn-primary&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt; to my markup to make it pretty and blue, and this is a common mistake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A primary button is the action that the user most likely going to be looking for. For example, if I&#39;m filling in a contact form, the primary action should be to submit it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having more than 1 primary buttons on a page creates noise, and is more likely to slow me down or cause me to make mistakes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there is a need for multiple buttons, decide which one is the primary and style the other ones differently. For example, having multiple grey buttons and one green button gives more weight to what might be the primary and secondary actions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, thinking about the content a little harder will make the design much easier to use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Buttons vs. links, what&#39;s the difference?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the land of user centred design, buttons and links are not interchangeable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of people make this mistake and litter the Internet with bad design which is confusing for the people that have to use it. Some of my early contributions are still out there causing a nuisance. Sorry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Buttons should trigger actions. They should interact with data. If you&#39;re submitting a form or deleting a comment, then a button is what to use. This is because you are taking data and doing something with it. Sending it, deleting it or saving it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Links are a means of navigating between pages. You may navigate to a form using a link, then submit it using a button.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;re styling links to look like buttons, you&#39;re perhaps making a mistake. But, if you&#39;re absolutely sure its not a mistake, at the very least make sure you change the role so that it remains accessible for users of assistive technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-html&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;a class=&amp;quot;btn&amp;quot; role=&amp;quot;button&amp;quot;&amp;gt;Subscribe to our mailing list&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By changing the role, it means if somebody using a voice controller says &#39;click button&#39;, it will still work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As always, I&#39;m happy to talk about this more if you&#39;re interested.&lt;/p&gt;

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>How to calculate reading time, like Medium</title>
    <link href="https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/how-to-calculate-reading-time-like-medium/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-31T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/how-to-calculate-reading-time-like-medium/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">
      &lt;h1&gt;How to calculate reading time, like Medium&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently, I took a leaf out of Medium&#39;s book and decided to add the estimated reading time to my blog posts. This was so that people could decide whether they had enough time to commit to the post before reading it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The task was pretty simple. It was only 7 lines of JavaScript. I wrote it and implemented it in a single train journey to Leeds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I tweeted about it, I got a request to write an explanation of the code. So here it goes!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below is the function. I&#39;ll go through each line of code and explain in detail what it does, so even if you&#39;re not using Node or Javascript, you can reverse engineer it for your language of choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-javascript&quot;&gt;function readingTime (text) {
  const wordsPerMinute = 200
  const noOfWords = text.split(/\s/g).length
  const minutes = noOfWords / wordsPerMinute
  const readTime = Math.ceil(minutes)
  return `${readTime} minute read`
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Step 1 - Declaring the function&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first line sets up the function, giving it the name &lt;code&gt;readingTime&lt;/code&gt;. It also tells it to expect an input which it can refer to as &lt;code&gt;text&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;text&lt;/code&gt; variable will be your article or blog post, as a string, that you want to calculate the reading time on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-javascript&quot;&gt;function readingTime(text) {}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Step 2 - Setting the number of words per minute&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next step is to create a variable called &lt;code&gt;wordsPerMinute&lt;/code&gt;, and set it to 200. The value is 200, because according to Google, that&#39;s the average number of words per minute a person can read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s obviously not going to be the same for everybody, but it seemed like a decent punt. In testing, Medium assumes you can read more. Their read time calculations were substantially faster than my calculations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I assume this is so that people aren&#39;t put off reading stuff on their platform, but I&#39;ve gone for a more realistic approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve used &lt;code&gt;const&lt;/code&gt; to declare my variables as I&#39;m using ES6 syntax, but you can also use &lt;code&gt;var&lt;/code&gt; if you prefer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-javascript&quot;&gt;function readingTime(text) {
  const wordsPerMinute = 200
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Step 3 - Calculating the number of words&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next step is the most complex. It&#39;s where we take the text and then calculate how many words it contains. There&#39;s actually 3 separate steps all chained together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, we call the &lt;code&gt;.split()&lt;/code&gt; method. We can call this on any string. It works by breaking the string up on a specific character you pass in, and it returns an array.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, &lt;code&gt;&#39;I-am-Craig&#39;.split(&#39;-&#39;)&lt;/code&gt; would return an array of &lt;code&gt;[&#39;I&#39;, &#39;am&#39;, &#39;Craig&#39;]&lt;/code&gt;. This is because I told it to split on a hyphen, so it went through and used the hyphens as the marker to create the array.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem is, article text isn&#39;t joined by hyphens. It will be joined by spaces, tabs, new lines, returns etc. So we&#39;re going to need to tell it to split on more than one thing. To do this, we use a regular expression, also known as regex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A regex will match a pattern rather than a single character. To define a regex, we put a pattern inside of two forward slashes. The pattern I used was &lt;code&gt;\s&lt;/code&gt;. This stands for whitespace, and it will match spaces, tabs, returns and newlines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, &lt;code&gt;/\s/&lt;/code&gt; would actually stop after finding the first whitespace character. So, we put a &lt;code&gt;g&lt;/code&gt; after the closing slash, which stands for global. This tells the regex to keep going to the end even if it has found a match.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to learn more about regex, You can play with patterns at &lt;a href=&quot;https://regex101.com/#javascript&quot;&gt;regex101.com/&lt;/a&gt;, and you can do an online course for free at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.codecademy.com/courses/javascript-intermediate-en-NJ7Lr/0/1&quot;&gt;Codecademy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once we have our regex pattern, we pass that into the &lt;code&gt;split()&lt;/code&gt; method from earlier. This will use any whitespace characters to break up the text, and return an array of all the words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, the last step is to count all the words in the array. To do that, we use the &lt;code&gt;.length&lt;/code&gt; property. This can be called on any array and will return a number. For example, our array from earlier &lt;code&gt;[&#39;I&#39;, &#39;am, &#39;Craig&#39;].length&lt;/code&gt; would return &lt;code&gt;3&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chain them all together and it will give you the number of words in your text.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-javascript&quot;&gt;function readingTime(text) {
  const wordsPerMinute = 200
  const noOfWords = text.split(/\s/g).length
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Step 4 - Calculate the read time in minutes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this step, create another new variable called minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Set it to be the number of words divided by the words per minute. This will calculate the average read time based on our 200 word per minute estimate from Google.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, &lt;code&gt;400 words / 200 words per minute&lt;/code&gt; would equal &lt;code&gt;2 minutes&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-javascript&quot;&gt;function readingTime(text) {
  const wordsPerMinute = 200;
  const noOfWords = text.split(/\s/g).length;
  const minutes = noOfWords / wordsPerMinute;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Step 5 - Rounding up the read time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whenever you&#39;re doing division, it&#39;s likely you won&#39;t get nice round numbers. You will usually end up with a decimal. We don&#39;t want to tell somebody it will take them 3.34 minutes to read an article, so we round the number.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve used the &lt;code&gt;.ceil()&lt;/code&gt; method to do this. This stands for ceiling, and it will round any decimals up to the nearest whole number. Because we&#39;re using ceiling it will only round up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-javascript&quot;&gt;Math.ceil(1)   // 1
Math.ceil(1.1) // 2
Math.ceil(1.9) // 2
Math.ceil(2)   // 2
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I chose to round up, as I thought it was better to over estimate than to under estimate. If you want to round down you can use &lt;code&gt;.floor()&lt;/code&gt; instead of &lt;code&gt;.ceil()&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only downside of using ceiling, is that passing in one word would still return a read time of 1 minute. However, I don&#39;t plan on doing any 1 word blog posts, so it shouldn&#39;t affect me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-javascript&quot;&gt;function readingTime(text) {
  const wordsPerMinute = 200
  const noOfWords = text.split(/\s/g).length
  const minutes = noOfWords / wordsPerMinute
  const readTime = Math.ceil(minutes)
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Step 6 - Return and finish&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that you have your rounded time in minutes, the last step is to return it from your function. To make it more readable, I&#39;ve added some words so if our read time was &lt;code&gt;2&lt;/code&gt;, the function would return &lt;code&gt;2 minute read&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve used backticks to declare my string, but you can do it using &lt;code&gt;readTime + &#39; minute read&#39;&lt;/code&gt; if you prefer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-javascript&quot;&gt;function readingTime(text) {
  const wordsPerMinute = 200
  const noOfWords = text.split(/\s/g).length
  const minutes = noOfWords / wordsPerMinute
  const readTime = Math.ceil(minutes)
  return `${readTime} minute read`
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Step 7 - Using your function&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that we&#39;ve got our function, we can call it by passing in any string to get a read time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-javascript&quot;&gt;const post = &#39;This is a test post&#39;
readingTime(post) // returns 1 minute read
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have any more questions, as always just reach out!&lt;/p&gt;

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Hear no, see no, techno</title>
    <link href="https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/hear-no-see-no-techno/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-31T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/hear-no-see-no-techno/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">
      &lt;h1&gt;Hear no, see no, techno&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week I attended &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wearesigma.com/campdigital/2017/&quot;&gt;Camp Digital&lt;/a&gt;, in the beautiful Town Hall of Manchester.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was your usual digital conference. Your usual crowd. But, today I saw a talk that has changed the way I think about websites and service design forever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By now, we all know websites have to be responsive. They have to be malleable, so that they look crisp and well laid out on all devices, and columns should stack when the viewport becomes narrow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We know the fonts need to scale on mobile devices, and that we may need to include higher resolution images for retina displays.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have this all figured out. But, we still assume people are always using the same devices we use and seeing the site the way that we see it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Accessibility matters&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&#39;Hear no, see no, techno&#39;, was an inspiring talk I attended by the incredible &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mollywatt.com/&quot;&gt;Molly Watt&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Molly spoke about how technology allows her to interact with the world and the web, despite the small barrier of being both blind and deaf!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Molly was born with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Usher_syndrome&quot;&gt;Usher Syndrome&lt;/a&gt;. She was born deaf, then became almost completely blind due to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Retinitis_pigmentosa&quot;&gt;retinitis pigmentosa&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the past, this would have made a lot of tasks impossible. But, here she stood, strong, independent, and educating us on how to do better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She delivered an amazing talk, interacting with the audience through the use of cochlear implants, which stream the audio straight into her head by converting sound waves into electrical impulses to stimulate the auditory nerve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She also wears an Apple Watch, and uses haptic feedback to navigate the city. Something as simple as making the watch vibrate to indicate whether its time to turn left or right seems so simple, but it&#39;s something most people, myself included, would overlook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Molly talked about things that are often not on a designers radar. For example, can you change the colours or the contrast of your website? Can you change the font size? The answer is probably not, unless it involves opening the stylesheet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Infinity scrolling is a damaging trend&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another thing I found fascinating was something as simple as a twitter widget. Twitter uses &#39;infinite scrolling&#39;, which means as you&#39;re scrolling and you approach the bottom, it loads in more tweets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is fine you are able to click away from the widget and continue your interaction with the site. But what if you&#39;re trying to &lt;kbd&gt;tab&lt;/kbd&gt; through the content using a keyboard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every time you &lt;kbd&gt;tab&lt;/kbd&gt; down a tweet, it loads in another one. And, because it is called &#39;infinite scrolling&#39;, you could be seven years deep in somebodies twitter feed by the time you get out!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Doing better&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I originally posted this on my old inaccessible WordPress blog. But thanks to Molly I&#39;ve made some changes. I plan to learn as much about accessibility as I can, so that I no longer disable people through bad design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As designers we often focus too much on making things look pretty. Instead, we should be making them available to everyone!&lt;/p&gt;

    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>What is &#39;normal&#39; anyway?</title>
    <link href="https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/what-is-normal-anyway/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-29T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.craigabbott.co.uk/blog/what-is-normal-anyway/</id>
    <content xml:lang="en" type="html">
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I want to be normal&lt;/em&gt;. How many people have muttered these words during times of turmoil? How many people have wanted to trade their noisy racing thoughts, for a brain that was more peaceful? A brain that was numb and void of opinion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know I have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I sit here, staring at the blank page, I can already feel my anxieties rising. As I begin to write, I find myself trying to imagine how anybody reading this will perceive my words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Type. Delete. Type. Delete.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem is, I rarely talk about these issues for fear of ridicule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m afraid that people won&#39;t take me seriously, or that they will brand me dramatic. I have suffered from depression and anxiety for as long as I can remember. Doctors, councillors, they all like to label stuff and hand out leaflets. Is it Cyclothymia. Maybe it&#39;s Bipolar 2. These are a few suggestions I&#39;ve had thrown at me to try and define my troubles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Professional people, friends, family, everyone has an opinion:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&#39;Cheer up mate.&#39;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&#39;What do &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; have to be down about?&#39;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&#39;Things can&#39;t be &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; bad!&#39;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Phrases like these are why I say nothing. Why I shuffle through life hiding the lows and pretending to be ok.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My anxieties go way back. The need for acceptance and the need to fit in is burned deep into my brain&#39;s limbic system. I can pretend to be confident. Bravado can get me so far. But then the armour cracks and that ugly viscous fluid of self-doubt slowly leaks out. It makes you forget who you are. It stains your soul and the very skin you are printed on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The problem is...&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have always known I was different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I grew up in Newcastle, often dubbed the party capital of the UK. Parties, fashion, clubbing, &#39;getting mortal&#39;, they are all part of normal life growing up here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hated it. But, if you didn&#39;t conform, people would brand you &#39;boring&#39;. There is no room for introverts here. You will simply be crushed under the egos of narcissistic juggernauts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Large crowds. Strangers. Drunk people. Rowdy and volatile situations. These are all things that send my anxieties through the roof. I spend most of the night on edge, analysing every detail of the room. Escape routes, possible threats, potential weapons. I have no control. And the only way to regain any is to analyse everything. To come up with a plan for every possible scenario.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can imagine, this is mentally exhausting, and I&#39;m usually ready for home well before midnight. But of course, you can&#39;t leave before midnight, because that&#39;s &lt;em&gt;&#39;boring&#39;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spent these times, the best part of a decade, finding ways to try and subdue my anxieties. Meanwhile, I was still trying to fit in and maintain the illusion that I was a &lt;em&gt;&#39;normal&#39;&lt;/em&gt; socialite. Trying to last until 4am when the clubs closed so I could be part of the taxi-queue victory parade for full-time partiers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now comes the bit I find difficult to admit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found the only way achieve this, was to not think about anything at all. It sounds simple enough. But for me, the only way to achieve this is to get so intoxicated that my brain didn&#39;t have the ability to think of anything to worry about. Or, at least, so it couldn&#39;t remember any of it in the morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking back, this behaviour made me hate myself. It made me selfish, angry and often unapproachable. I would spend my nights unable to sleep and my days unable to get out of bed. I would snap at anybody that attempted to save me from myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I look out on my past, relationships lay wrecked in my field of view. Dashed upon the rocks for failing to navigate the fierce storm of my self-destruction. I wasn&#39;t addressing the issue. I was abusing a coping mechanism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trouble with a coping mechanism is that it never addresses the problem. It doesn&#39;t ever make you feel better. It just delays the onset of despair. And amplifies it when it arrives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Creative people tend to think more. And, by this, I don&#39;t mean they&#39;re more intelligent. I don&#39;t mean that if you don&#39;t identify as creative that you have nothing going on between your ears. I just mean creative people are more likely to dwell on something that others may overlook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Creative people pay attention to things in far greater detail. While this is our gift, it is also our curse. Attention to detail is the difference between painting a picture and a masterpiece. But it is also this attention to detail that makes us ruminate. It is the reason we can&#39;t let go easily. The reason we play scenarios out in our heads over and over again. The reason we can always see how we could have done things better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is this ruminating that is often the catalyst for depression. Or at least, it is in my case. The constant battle with yourself to be better. The over analytical views you take of your work or yourself. The feeling that you don&#39;t deserve any credit you receive. These feelings are all too real in our industry. Because in this industry, it is rare for you to come up with anything on your own. Clients give briefs to designers. Designers then give work to developers. When you reach the end of a project, it is often easy to feel like the team has carried you, or that they have handed you an idea. My councillor would label this &#39;imposter syndrome&#39;. It is the inability to accept an accomplishment, despite the external evidence staring you in the face.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;So how do we deal with this?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Learn to internalise any external verification&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When somebody compliments you, believe it and take it on board. Very few people hand out lies as compliments, so if they tell you they like your work, it&#39;s likely that they do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Say thank you, pat yourself on the back, and don&#39;t always dwell on what you felt you could have done better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Surround yourself with positive, like-minded people&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If people are negative, stop taking their comments on board. Don&#39;t associate with those who negatively impact your life or make you feel anxious about being yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest problems in my life was believing I had lots of friends, when in fact, I had lots of acquaintances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#39;s a great quote by Goi Nasu, which is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&#39;An entire sea of water can&#39;t sink a ship unless it gets inside the ship. Similarly, the negativity of the world can&#39;t put you down unless you allow it to get inside you.&#39;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Don&#39;t suffer in silence&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have any doubts, anxieties, or if you are feeling depressed, talk to somebody. Hell, reach out and talk to me!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes lifting the lid off it all makes the load seem lighter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Look for flaws in others&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&#39;t mean this in the sense that you should make things difficult for people, or point out their mistakes. But notice to yourself that they do make mistakes, and realise that this is what humans do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Understand that you are not alone. Nobody is perfect, and recognising this can help you to come to terms with your mistakes when you make them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Discover your fears&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All anxieties stem from fear. You need to work out what it is that you&#39;re afraid of and make an action plan to try and conquer it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Discover what makes you happy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most people think more money will make them happy. But the depression doesn&#39;t go away no matter how much money they make.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, I&#39;m most happy when I&#39;m helping people. The Joker says &#39;if you&#39;re good at something never do it for free.&#39; But, if I can donate my time, or something I&#39;m no longer using, and it genuinely helps somebody, that brings me more joy than the token amount of money I&#39;d probably charge for it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Don&#39;t conform&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don&#39;t want to do something, then don&#39;t do it. I am now teetotal because I don&#39;t enjoy drinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I&#39;m honest with myself, I never have enjoyed it. It was a coping mechanism that is no longer needed. People may think it is boring. So what? In fact, people often have more of an issue with me &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; drinking, then I do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Be true to yourself&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is probably the most important point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wear the clothes you want to wear, rather than what society has told you is cool! Be passionate about the things that interest you rather that whatever is popular at the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Individuality is what makes us human. We should embrace and celebrate the fact that everybody is different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How can you ever escape depression with the suppression of who you are? How can you ever be happy with yourself if you are pretending to be somebody else?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don&#39;t agree with any of these points, then that is fine. I&#39;m at a point in my life where I don&#39;t feel like I need your approval!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am what I am, not what you would like me to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article was part of &lt;a href=&quot;http://geekmentalhelp.com/&quot;&gt;Geek Mental Help&lt;/a&gt; Week. It&#39;s a week-long series of articles, blog posts, conversations, podcasts and events across the web about mental health issues, how to help people who suffer, and those who care for us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading,
Craig&lt;/p&gt;

    </content>
  </entry>
</feed>